<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A three fold help to political observations contained in three discourses. Written by that learned and experienced gentleman, Sir Jsaac Wake. 1. The first concerning the thirteen cantons of the Helvetical League, or of the Switzers. 2. The second declaring the state of Italy, as it stood neer about the year 1625. 3. The third touching the proceedings of the King of Sweden in his wars in Germany. Published for the benefit of the diligent observer.</title>
            <author>Wake, Isaac, Sir, 1580?-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1671_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208410</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867365</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96533)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 209:E1671[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A three fold help to political observations contained in three discourses. Written by that learned and experienced gentleman, Sir Jsaac Wake. 1. The first concerning the thirteen cantons of the Helvetical League, or of the Switzers. 2. The second declaring the state of Italy, as it stood neer about the year 1625. 3. The third touching the proceedings of the King of Sweden in his wars in Germany. Published for the benefit of the diligent observer.</title>
                  <author>Wake, Isaac, Sir, 1580?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 119, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Andrew Crook, at the signe of the green Dragon in St. Pauls Church-yeard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June: 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Italy --  Politics and government --  1559-1789 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Switzerland --  Politics and government --  1499-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Switzerlnad --  Politics and government --  1648-1789 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Three fold Help TO POLITICAL OBSERVATIONS Contained in three DISCOVRSES.</p>
            <p>Written by that learned and experienced Gentleman, <hi>Sir Jſaac Wake.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The firſt concerning the thirteen Cantons of the Helvetical Leagve, Or of the Switzers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The ſecond declaring the State of Italy, as it ſtood neer about the year</hi> 1625.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>The third touching the proceedings of the King of</hi> Sweden <hi>in his Wars in</hi> Germany.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Publiſhed for the benefit of the diligent Obſerver.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> at the ſigne of the green <hi>Dragon</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yeard. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119672:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119672:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here preſented to thine own, and the publick view, three diſtinct treatiſes, written upon ſeveral ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and ſeveral occaſions; But becauſe they have all one Author, and were not much different in time, and eſpecially becauſe (though they ſeem ſtrangers in their
<pb facs="tcp:119672:3"/>Titles) yet there is a kinde of affinitie in the ſubject matter of them, as being all deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, of ſeveral parts and provinces, and bearing equal Marks of judgement, and pollicie in affaires of ſtate. It was thought fit to binde them up together, that ſo they might become more conſiderable in the ſale, to him that was to bear the charge of printing them, and likewiſe yeeld more variety of pleaſure and content, if not of profit and advantage to the judicious Reader: for though it hath been ſaid by ſome, that things of this nature, when once they are known do loſe the eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:119672:3"/>we had of them before, yet certainly an active un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding man will finde a way to enlarge his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, by the uſe of them, upon future occaſions, when they ſhall be offered. For otherwiſe, what benefit ſhal we reap by Hiſtory, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of al kinds, or any practick knowledge, which we ſhall attain unto? though both the State of theſe Provinces and the affairs, and relations of the World, as to them, have ſuffered many great al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, ſince theſe treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were written, yet ſuch are the continual viciſſitude, and changes of all ſublunarie things, as though it be not
<pb facs="tcp:119672:4"/>probable we ſhall ever ſee them ſetled in all points as they were before, yet may they come ſo neer either in the ſame, or other parts, as that theſe obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may ſerve as land-marks by which we may ſteer our courſe in the like conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</p>
            <p>The Author of all theſe three treatiſes was Sir <hi>Iſaac Wake,</hi> a man of exquiſite hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning, ſtrong parts of nature, and a moſt refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wit, able to penetrate into the depth of things, and give a judgement on them, grounded upon ſolid reaſon: Theſe parts, both of nature and learning, aſſiſted with a
<pb facs="tcp:119672:4"/>neat expreſſion of his own conceptions, not onely in the Latine tongue (wherein he was excellent) but alſo in the vulgar languages, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a logical inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, made all his compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures not onely Methodical, but pleaſing and perſpicuous</p>
            <p>To all theſe may be added, as the Crown of all, his long experience in affaires of ſtate, as having been many yeers emploied an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour abroad to forreign Princes, both by king <hi>James,</hi> and the late king <hi>Charles,</hi> wherein he behaved himſelf ſo dexterouſly, &amp; judiciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as not onely gave ful ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to his Maſters, but
<pb facs="tcp:119672:5"/>procured him love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from all thoſe Princes, and Republicks, with whom he was to negotiate, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to that credit, and reputation amongſt them which did much facillitate the expedition of affaires to his Maſters honor (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was ever moſt Jeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) and his own deſerved-commendation. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may obſerve in the firſt of theſe treatieſes, a particular example of his admirable dexterity, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediting the moſt intricate affaires, when they were held almoſt inextricable. That Gordion knot (as he calls it) about the <hi>Pais de
<pb facs="tcp:119672:5"/>Vaud,</hi> which (notwithſtand the interpoſition of moſt of the potent Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom) continued fourty years, without finding any man that could unlooſe it, was by his miniſtery, and not ordinary endeavour, at laſt untied; and though he out of Modeſtie and dutie, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe all this (and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly) to the wiſdom and felicity of his Maſters Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: yet the judicions reader may obſerve that excellent <hi>temperamentum</hi> to which this difficult buſineſſe was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced through the ripeneſſe of his Wit and judgement, wherby it was at laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.
<pb facs="tcp:119672:6"/>Having ſaid thus much of the worthy Author (of whom much more might yet be ſaid, if it were fit to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in a Preface.) There will be no need to ſpeak much of the treatiſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their own worth wil bring both delight and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to the obſerving Reader. The firſt of them may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps appear to him the moſt exact and perfect deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe parts, which hath hitherto been offered to the publick view.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was peculiarly proper to our induſtrious Author, whoſe conſtant courſe it was, upon all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable changes, and alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
<pb facs="tcp:119672:6"/>either at home or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the Provinces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his charge, to give a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary relation of all affaires tranſacted there, and of their ends and intereſts, who ſat at the ſtern to guide them, by which means his Maſters and their Miniſters of ſtate at home, received great light and information, how to ſteer their courſe, and give directions to their publick Miniſters abroad. The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit which accrues from theſe general relations, is remarkable in the ſtate of Venice, whoſe Ambaſſadors are bound to give an exact account to that grave, and wary Senate, of the
<pb facs="tcp:119672:7"/>Condition and intereſts of all thoſe Provinces where they reſide, and when they return home, to give a full relation in writing, of the State and condition of thoſe parts, as they ſtood when they departd from them, and theſe are carefully kept in Archivis for their future uſe and information.</p>
            <p>The laſt of theſe three diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes (it muſt be confeſt) may ſeem imperfect, yet is it compoſed with ſo much ſound judgement grounded upon reaſon, and experience as may give the dilignt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a full and perfect view, of the Motives which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeded, and the ends to
<pb facs="tcp:119672:7"/>which the proceedings of that glorious king of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> were directed. It hath ben held a piece of policie in the Ancients, to leave all their great and magnificent works in ſome one part or other unfiniſhed, that ſo there might be <hi>Deſideratum quid</hi> ſomething for deſire to long after, and wiſh for, till it be ſatiſfied, the want whereof, works is us ſo great an eſtimation of that which appears admirable in it ſelf, as that it ſeems a pittie, that it was not brought to ful perfection. But when once the minde of man is fully ſatisfied, our admiration ceaſeth, and with it the
<pb facs="tcp:119672:8"/>value, and eſteem of that which once we did admire; it cannot be reaſonably ſuppoſed, that in ſo ſhort &amp; ſuccinct a piece as this, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ambition could cauſe the Author to leave it imperfect; But yet the want of that which ſhould have been the concluſion and application of the whole diſcourſe, may haply ſtir up ſome active brain, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that defect, and it may perhaps be thought no point of defficulty, for one acquainted with thoſe times out of theſe premiſes, to draw a right concluſion. Onely it is to be feared, that it may prove like that
<pb facs="tcp:119672:8"/>
               <hi>Capo di venere</hi> (as the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans tearm it) that unparra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld <hi>Head of Venus,</hi> cut out, and delineated with exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Art and Beauty by that rare ſtatuarie, who inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to have fitted the whole body to it, but was prevented by death: and though there were then, and bave been ſince, many excellent Artiſts in that kinde, yet ſuch was the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and admirable ſculpture of that <hi>Head,</hi> that no man ever after, durſt put a hand to finiſh what was left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</p>
            <p>However (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) if thou finde either Content, or profit in this
<pb facs="tcp:119672:9"/>or either of the other two Diſcourſes; Thine be the benefit, and mine the pain. And ſo I bid thee hartily farewell, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy loving friend <hi>IGNOTUS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119672:9"/>
                  <head>A DISCOVRSE OF THE Thirteen Cantons OF THE HELVETICAL LEAGUE</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He 13. Cantons of the Helvetical League are theſe, <hi>Zurick, Berne, Lucerne, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rie, Swits, Underwald, Zug, Glaris, Baſil, Friburg, Soloure, Schaphuſen, Appenzeil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of theſe, four are wholy of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, namly, <hi>Zurick, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Schaphuſen.</hi> Two are mixt, namely <hi>Glaris</hi> and <hi>Appenzeil,</hi> but the greater part in both thoſe Cantons are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119672:10"/>Proteſtants, and generally they do concur with the four above named towns.</p>
                  <p>The Popiſh Cantons are in number ſeven, <hi>Lucerne, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rie, Swits, Underwald, Zug, Friburg, and Soleure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt that did Cantonize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were <hi>Vrie, Swits,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderwald,</hi> in the year 1308. upon occaſion of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rany which the houſe <hi>Auſtria</hi> did exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe upon them, which firſt League was afterward more ſolemly confirmed by a publick Act, ſigned and ſealed at <hi>Brunen</hi> in the yeer 1315.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucerne</hi> was the next that entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Alliance, in the yeer 1332. The name of <hi>Lucerne</hi> was given to that Town upon occaſion of a Lantern, or beacon that did ſhine there in the night, to give light to thoſe that did paſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the lake.</p>
                  <p>After <hi>Lucerne, Zurick</hi> did Colleague it ſelf with the four Cantons above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, Anno 1351. and had the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be ranged in the firſt place, by reaſon of the greatneſſe of the Town, which was very famous in thoſe dayes, and ſtill it doth hold the chief rank a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the thirteen Cantons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Glaris</hi> did enter into this Alliance in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119672:10"/>the year 1352. and the ſame year <hi>Zug</hi> was likewiſe Cantonized 1352. The year following 1353, <hi>Berne</hi> entred into the ſame aſſociation, beginning with <hi>Uri, Swits</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderwald,</hi> which three Cantons did oblige themſelves to <hi>Zurick</hi> and <hi>Lucerne,</hi> to ſuccour them when they ſhould need, and to bring with them thoſe of <hi>Berne,</hi> if <hi>Zurick</hi> and <hi>Lucerne</hi> ſhould require it, as likewiſe <hi>Zurick</hi> and <hi>Lucerne</hi> did promiſe to aſſiſt <hi>Berne,</hi> when the three Cantons ſhould ſummon them thereunto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Friburgh</hi> made firſt Allliance with <hi>Berne,</hi> Anno 1403. and by their means were joyned to the other Cantons, upon certain conditions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Soleure</hi> entred likewiſe firſt into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation with <hi>Berne</hi> Anno 1351. and held good correſpondence with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cantons afterward having aſſiſted the other <hi>Swiſſes</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> they and <hi>Friburg</hi> together were taken into the number of the other Cantons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> was made a Canton Anno. 1501 and received into a perpetual. confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all the body of the <hi>Swiſſes; Schaphuſen</hi> made firſt Alliance with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119672:11"/>ſome of the leſſer Cantons, for tearm of years, and laſtly, Anno 1501. that Town was taken into the general league Helvetick: the name of this Town is taken from <hi>Scapha,</hi> or <hi>Skiffe,</hi> as being ſeated upon the Rhine in the midſt of certain rocks, which cauſe the river to to precipitate ſike a torrent, by reaſon whereof it is impaſſable, ſo that al boats that come from the lake of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> are forced to unlade there &amp; from the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of boats, the Town taketh his name.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appenſel</hi> is a Village ſituared under <hi>San Gallo,</hi> a great Town on the frontire of the <hi>Griſons;</hi> In this village the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of <hi>San Gallo</hi> was wont to reſide, and from thence the village dotl: derive his name, <hi>Appenzel</hi> being as much as <hi>Abbatis Cella.</hi> The inhabitants did firſt ſet themſelves at liberty by force of arms, and afterwards they did pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe both their peace and freedom with a great ſum of money, whicd they did pay unto the Abbot. Their firſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance was with <hi>Zurick, Lucerne, Swits, Underwald, Zug</hi> and <hi>Glaris,</hi> and in the year 1513 they were received into the number of the Cantons.</p>
                  <p>The Alliances that the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119672:11"/>with their neighbours are theſe; firſt with the Abbot and Town of <hi>San Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo;</hi> Secondly with the <hi>Griſons;</hi> Thirdly with the <hi>Valeſiens,</hi> Fourthly with <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toille,</hi> Fifty with <hi>Mulhouſe,</hi> Sixtly with <hi>Bienne,</hi> Seventhly with <hi>Geneva,</hi> Laſtly with <hi>Neufchaſtel,</hi> which confederations are not in general with the body of the <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> but particular with particular Cantons; ſome Cantons having taken ſome of the above named Towns into their Conbourgioſie, and others taken other ſome; the <hi>Griſons</hi> are allied with all, and have beſides particular alliance more ſtraight with ſome particular Cantons.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Baliages.</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Baliages</hi> that are governed in common by the thirteen Cantons, or the greater part of them are theſe: <hi>Turgow, Bade,</hi> the <hi>Rhegujces,</hi> called in their Language <hi>Rhintal, Sargans:</hi> the free Countrey <hi>Lugano, Locarne, Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driſe,</hi> the vally of <hi>Madia,</hi> and <hi>Bellinſone:</hi> of theſe <hi>Rhintal</hi> and <hi>Sargans</hi> confine with the <hi>Griſons,</hi> and ſpeak that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. <hi>Lugano, Locarne, Mendriſe</hi> the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119672:12"/>
                        <hi>valley of Madia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bellinſone,</hi> are beyond the <hi>Alpes,</hi> on the othet ſide of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains <hi>San Gotard,</hi> and <hi>San Bernard;</hi> the other three, namely <hi>Turgoro, Bade,</hi> and the free Countrey are properly <hi>Swiſſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All the Cantons have not equal au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over theſe <hi>Balliages,</hi> but as their aſſociations were made in divers times, ſo likewiſe the right of the Cantons is divers.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Turgoro</hi> is commanded by the ſeven firſt and moſt ancient Cantons, namely, <hi>Zurick, Lucerne Vri, Swits, Vnderwald, Zug,</hi> and <hi>Glaris</hi> who do alternatively ſend Bailifs thither, but <hi>Berne, Friburg</hi> and <hi>Soleure,</hi> have likewiſe ſome little right in cauſes criminal.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bade</hi> is ſubject to the ſame ſeven Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, and <hi>Berne, Sargans, Rhintal</hi> and the free Countrey is likewiſe governed by the firſt ſeven Cantons, onely in the government of <hi>Rhintal</hi> they have given part to <hi>Appenſel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The four <hi>Balliages</hi> beyond the hils, namely, <hi>Lugano, Locarne, Mendriſe,</hi> and the valley of <hi>Madia,</hi> is ſubject to all the Cantons except <hi>Appenſel,</hi> who have nothing to do there, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantoniſed, after the winning of thoſe places.</p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119672:12"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bellinſone</hi> is ſubject onely to <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri, Swits</hi> and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderwald,</hi> every one of which Cantons hath a Caſtlel or Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del in the Town, commanded by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Officer of their own.</p>
                     <p>That which they call the free Province is certain Caſtles and Villages ſituated along the river of Ruſs, above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Bremgarten,</hi> the names of the chief Villages are <hi>Meyenberg, Richenſce</hi> and <hi>Ergow,</hi> which ancienly had their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction and their Magiſtrate apart, whereupon they were called <hi>les Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces libres.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The greateſt part of theſe Provinces were ſubject formerly to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and in the reign of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> when <hi>Frederick</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> conteſted with him, the ſaid Emperour perſwaded the <hi>Switſes</hi> to take arms againſt <hi>Frederick,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them that they ſhould retain whatſoever they could conquer over <hi>Frederick</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> by which right they hold the moſt of their <hi>Bailliages,</hi> on this ſide the hills.</p>
                     <p>As for the places which they hold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Alpes,</hi> their right is ſomewhat queſtionable: they pretend that in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119672:13"/>year 1513, when they did help <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian Sforza</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan</hi> to chaſe the <hi>French</hi> out of <hi>Italy,</hi> he did in liew of their aſſiſtance give them the four <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liages</hi> confining with their Countrey, namly<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Lugan</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from <hi>Milan</hi> N N W <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> a point W. 47. Miles, and being prodigal of his name com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates it to a lake called the lake <hi>Lugan</hi> which tendeth N. and S. and is in length 20. Miles, and where it is broadeſt 8. Miles, and narroweſt 3. Miles.</note> 
                        <hi>Lugano,</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Locarne</hi> lieth from <hi>Lugan</hi> 20. Miles N.N.W. and is ſituated at the Weſtern ſide of the great Lake, called in that reſpect <hi>il Lago Maggiore</hi> which tendeth N. N. E. and S. and by W. and is in length 47. Miles and breadth 7. Miles.</note> 
                        <hi>Locarne, Mendriſe,</hi> and the valley of<note n="c" place="margin">The <hi>Val de Madia</hi> lieth between <hi>Mont S Gotardo</hi> (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led anciently by <hi>Ptolome Adula,</hi> more modernly <hi>Dogel,</hi> and now as formerly, in regard of a little Church built in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to that Saint <hi>Gotardo</hi>) and the lake <hi>Maggiore,</hi> it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth N. N. W. and S. S. E. 40. Miles in length, and 7. broad. The town <hi>Madia</hi> ſtandeth by a River of that name, which confineth the Valley.</note> 
                        <hi>Madia,</hi> and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward <hi>Francis</hi> the great when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the ſtate of <hi>Milan,</hi> did confirm unto the <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> the former donation of <hi>Maximilian Sforza,</hi> by a publick Act paſſed at <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>burg.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But in a relation that I have ſeen of the State of <hi>Milan,</hi> I finde that they are accuſed to have uſurped thoſe places, in the time of <hi>Lewes</hi> the 12. King of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119672:13"/>
                        <hi>France, il quale</hi> (ſaith my Authour) <hi>havendo guadagnato to ſtato di</hi> Milano, <hi>&amp;</hi> Licentiato <hi>li</hi> Swiſſer <hi>chi havenano Jeruiti in quella impreſa, &amp; fatto loro ogni dimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratione di gratitudine, non ſolo con gl'in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieri pagamenti, ma con molti doni et pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioni, queſſi medeſimi ritornandoſene à ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa occuparono Belintina inſolentiſſimam le, non aſſignando altra ragione di quel che fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenano, che l'ſſere loro neceſſaria quella pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alla, per aprirſi il paſſo allo ſtato di Milano, quando haveſſero voluto entrarui ſenla ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlo a dimandare ad altro Principe. &amp; enſtandi il Re Luigi per la reſtitutione, riſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſero ſuperbiſſimamle: che volevano an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che la Murata, &amp; Lucarno appreſſo, per farſi pin facile l'entrata in</hi> Italia <hi>a voglia loro, &amp; coſi lo piſero in eſſecutione &amp;c. Teſoro Politico</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                        <hi>parte fol.</hi> 295. <hi>impreſs. Francofort.</hi> 1610.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Which comes in Engliſh thus.</head>
                     <p>Who (ſaith my Authour) having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the State of <hi>Milan,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> to depart, that had ſerved him in that enterpriſe, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all demonſtrations of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, not onely by allowing them their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119672:14"/>whole paie, but by many gifts and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, beſtowed amongſt them. Thoſe very men returning home, moſt inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſurpriſed <hi>Belinſone,</hi> giving no other reaſon for it, but that the place was verie neceſſary for them, to open their paſſage into the State of <hi>Milan,</hi> when they had occaſion to paſſe that way, that ſo they might not be compell'd to demand it from other <hi>Princes.</hi> And King <hi>Lewis</hi> uſing all means poſſible for the reſtitution of it, They moſt proudly anſwered, that they would alſo have <hi>Murata</hi> and <hi>Lucarne</hi> ere it were long to make their paſſage into <hi>Italy</hi> more eaſie at their own pleaſure, and this they brought to paſſe &amp;c. <hi>Teſoro Politico</hi> i<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                        <hi>part. fol.</hi> 295. printed at <hi>Erancofort</hi> 1610.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Swiſſes forein Alliances</head>
                     <p>Among the Alliances which the <hi>Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> have at this preſent, the moſt ancient is that with the houſe of <hi>Aſtria,</hi> which is hereditary and perpetual, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with all the thirteen Cantons; they receive no penſion, <hi>non deniers de Paix,</hi> as they call it, this for Alliance, in regard
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119672:14"/>that the <hi>Auſtriaci</hi> do buy the League dear enough in letting the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy peaceable what they have conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the dominions belonging hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſecond general Alliance that the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> have with forein Princes, is that which is contracted betwixt their whole body, &amp; the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> for which the French King doth pay in yearly pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions the value of 30000 franks, which is divided among the ſeveral Cantons by a Geometrical proportion, and not Arithmetical; for every Canton doth not ſhare alike, of theſe <hi>Deniers de Paix,</hi> but they have ſome more, ſome leſſe, according as ſome are able to contribute more men then others to the ſervice of that Crown.</p>
                     <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and his houſe, hath a general Alliance with the whole Helvetian body, which is called <hi>une League de regarde</hi> containing no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reſtriction to defenſive or offenſive ſuccor one of the other, but onely fair and good correſpondence befitting neighbours, whoſe ſtates are confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
                     <p>With the Catholick Cantons the ſaid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119672:15"/>Duke hath a particular league, namely with <hi>Lucerne, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri, Swits, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderwald, Zug</hi> and <hi>Friburg,</hi> of whom he is to have ſix thouſand men for his ſervice at his own coſt, in caſe of defence, and in lieu thereof he doth pay to thoſe Cantons the yeerly ſum of 9. thouſand <hi>dueatons,</hi> which is diſtributed likewiſe by unequal portions, and part thereof is allotted to the common treaſury of every one of thoſe Cantons, part to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are of moſt credit and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in their Countrey. This league was made in the year 1579. in the time of the Duke <hi>Emmanuel Philibert,</hi> and the durance thereof is expreſſed to be, during the life of the ſaid Duke, and of his ſon <hi>Charles Emmanuel</hi> now living, and ten years after his death.</p>
                     <p>The king of <hi>Spain</hi> hath a league with the fore-named ſix cantons Catholicks, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly <hi>Lncerne, Uri, Swits, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderwald, Zug,</hi> and <hi>Friburg,</hi> and likewiſe with <hi>Apenſel,</hi> which is a mixt Canton, conſiſting half of Proteſtants, and half of Papiſts; He doth pay in continuation of this Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance an yearly penſion of fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>ducatons,</hi> which is divided betwixt the Treaſuries of each Canton, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119672:15"/>particular perſons, <hi>proportione Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> and he is to have of them all for the defence of the State of <hi>Milan</hi> ſix thouſand men, at his own charge. This league was contracted <hi>Anno</hi> 1589. in the time of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lip</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and is to laſt during his life, and his ſon the King that now reigneth, and ten yeares after both their deaths.</p>
                     <p>When this league was firſt made, <hi>Spain</hi> had ſmall credit in this Countrey, and the French crown was only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected there, inſomuch that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was inforced to deſire the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who is now alive, to interpoſe his authority, which was great with that people, for the effecting of that Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Howſoever the French Miniſters did at that time oppoſe themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it with ſuch heat, that the league was made with conditions as diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to <hi>Spain</hi> as might be, namely, barely defenſive for the State of <hi>Milan,</hi> in caſe of invaſion, ſince that time the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (according to the cuſtom of that nation) have incroached a great deal, and by the help of the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> they procured in the year 1604 a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of certain articles contained in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119672:16"/>the firſt league, which they did get to be extended more to their advantage then the intent was at the firſt, and in particular they obtained a ſpecification of the paſſage to be granted through the State of the Cantons, for al ſtrangers whom the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould have occaſion to leavy for his ſervice in <hi>Italy.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador did ſtrongly oppoſe againſt that declaration at that time, but all that he could obtain was a reſervation of the right of the <hi>French</hi> King, and that the ſaid declaration ſhould be underſtood not to prejudice in any thing the Alliance that the <hi>French</hi> King hath with that people.</p>
                     <p>Since that time the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> piſtols pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more weighty then the <hi>French</hi> crowns, <hi>Alfonſo Caſati</hi> Ambaſſador for the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in thoſe parts, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Canton of <hi>Uri,</hi> (in whoſe hands the paſſage is) a new declaration in the yeer 1616 in favour of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> league, without reſervation of the exception formerly interpoſed by the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, to the notable preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the publick liberty. Monſieur <hi>Vigier,</hi> who was reſident in <hi>Swiſſerland</hi>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119672:16"/>at that time, in the abſence of Monſieur <hi>de Caſtille,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be much offended with that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation, and threatened to proteſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly againſt the Canton of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri,</hi> but when the publick Diet was held at <hi>Bada,</hi> in the moneth of <hi>Iune</hi> the ſame year, though the matter was then freſh, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that the Lands-Knights were but newly paſſed at that time into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> under the conduct of the <hi>Count Carlo Lodovico di Solz;</hi> Monſieur <hi>Vigier</hi> held his peace, and ſaid nothing, having (as is imagined) received order out of <hi>France</hi> not to oppoſe himſelf againſt any thing that the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> ſhould do, by means of which connivence the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> party hath got ſo much ground, that hereafter it will not be in the power of <hi>France</hi> to counterpoiſe them, when they ſhall in theſe parts attempt any thing that may prove a diſſervice of the <hi>French</hi> King or Crown. <hi>Ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> enim ibi conſistunt exempla ubi ceperunt, ſed quemlibet in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuem recepta tramitem, latiſſime evagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ſibi viam faciunt:</hi> an evident proof whereof we ſee in the incroaching of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in theſe parts, for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as at the firſt they did not dare to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119672:17"/>the point of the paſſage in their Alliance, they did begin (as hath been noted above) in the year 1604. by way of explanation of their articles, to draw in the benefit of the paſſage, but which reſervation of the right of <hi>France,</hi> in the year 1616. they renewed their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, without reſerving the right of the <hi>French,</hi> and this year 1617. they have gone ſo far, as to take the point of the paſſage, for a thing granted, and without asking leave of the eight Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, who have equal juriſdiction at <hi>Bada,</hi> or of the twelve Cantons, who have the ſame right in the <hi>Bailliages</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the hills, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour hath treated the buſineſſe onely with the Catholick Cantons, who are all now at his devotion, and in ſcorn of the Proteſtant Cantons, he did write letters to <hi>Zurick, Berne,</hi> and the reſt, which did onely advertiſe that the <hi>Wallons</hi> which <hi>Don Verdugo</hi> did conduct to the ſervice of the king of <hi>Spain</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> were to paſſe through places of their juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that therefore they ſhould do well to ſee them provided of victualls, and al ſuch things as they ſhould want, without uſing a word of entreaty or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119672:17"/>requeſt in his letters, as if thoſe had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do in the buſineſs: as he hath at this preſent excluded the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Cantons from having any thing to do in granting the paſſage through Towns ſubject to their juriſdiction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Catholicks have the plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of voices, ſo will he hereafter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude likewiſe the Catholick Cantons, having already laid the foundation of that deſigne; for, in his propoſition this year 1617. in the moneth of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril,</hi> at <hi>Lucerne,</hi> he demanded paſſage of the little Cantons, for four thouſand foot onely, and 1000. horſe, without arms, and to paſſe by 200. at a time, a dayes journey diſtant the one from the other, &amp; notwithſtanding that his grant was for no more, and in the form ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, he cauſed 6000. Wallons to paſſe and 1000. horſe, together with their arms, ſo that hereafter he will alledg this example, that as this year there have paſſed two thouſand without leave ſo hereafter he may cauſe as many as he liſt to paſſe, and never ask licence for them, but take the matter as a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready granted and accuſtomed. This league is now upon the point of expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119672:18"/>for the ten years after the death of <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, and his ſon <hi>Philip</hi> the third are almoſt run out, and therefore it will ſhortly appear upon the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this league, whether the French will be ſo wiſe as to oppoſe againſt the above ſpecified incroachments, or the Swiſſes ſo careful of their publick liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as to reſtrain it within the limits of the bounds preſcribed in the beginning. As <hi>France</hi> is now governed, it is not likely that oppoſition will be made on that ſide, conſidering that the Miniſters of that Crown, do viſibly in all places cooperat towards the aggrandiſing of the Spaniards; and as for the Catholick Swiſſes, it may be ſaid as truly as it was ſaid of <hi>Rome, O vrbem venalem &amp; ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò perituram, ſi emptorem invenerit?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zurick</hi> and <hi>Berne</hi> have a particular league with the Marquis of <hi>Baden,</hi> and <hi>Turlach,</hi> contracted in the year 1612. during the life of the Marquis, and of Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> his ſon, and ten years after. It is meerly defenſive, and as each of thoſe Cantons are to give him for his defence 1000. men at his charge, ſo he is bound to furniſh them with the like proportion, at his charge, or ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119672:18"/>much money, the choice being left unto them, whether they will have men or money. This league is ſtill on foot, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Marquis hath loſt moſt of his eſtate, for the Emperour hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted a Nephew of the Marquis, called <hi>Edward</hi> in the Marquiſate of <hi>Baden,</hi> and although Prince <hi>Frederic,</hi> his eldeſt ſon is ſuffered to enjoy the Marquiſat of <hi>Turlach,</hi> in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Duke of <hi>Wirtenberg,</hi> whoſe ſiſter he hath married, and whom the Emperour is unwilling to diſpleaſe, yet <hi>Tilly</hi> and <hi>Verdugo</hi> do lodg and quarter troops there at their pleaſure, ſo that the Prince doth hold it, but as it were <hi>precariò.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Canton of <hi>Berne</hi> hath an Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and league apart with the houſe of <hi>Savoy,</hi> contracted in the year 1617. betwixt that State and <hi>Charles Emanü<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and it is to laſt during his life, the life of the Prince of <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and ten years after. They are bound to furniſh <hi>Savoy</hi> with 3000. foot at his coſt, and for the defence onely of his eſtates, and he is obliged to give them 2000. foot, and 500. horſe, or ſo much money, when the neceſſity of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119672:19"/>ſhall require it. The birth of this league may be called <hi>partus elephantinus,</hi> in regard that it had been treated forty year before it could be concluded. The French King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth did interpoſe himſelf twice as an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but could not bring it to concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The whole body of the Helvetical Cantons, did imbrace it likewiſe divers times, but could never prevail, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it was referred unto the Valeſani, as to a Republick neareſt confining, and ſtrictly allied with both the parties, yet after many years negotiation, and much paines they could effect nothing. In the year above named 1617. King <hi>James</hi> of glorious memory did interpoſe his authority, and as he had a particular genius which did incline him to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the accommodation of all miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings among all Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and States, ſo God did miraculouſſy bleſſe thoſe pious intentions of his, and in this particular his Majeſty had the honour not onely to extinguiſh that mortal hatred which had raigned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hove 60 yeares, betwixt the houſe of <hi>Savoy</hi> and that State, but to joyn and unite them in a ſtrict bond of league and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119672:19"/>Allyance. The tranſaction of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe in it ſelf is very conſiderable, in regard that ſo many had ſo long time travelled in that vineyard, and never reaped any fruit of honour, whereas his Majeſtie employing his ſervant Sir <hi>Iſaae Wake</hi> thither in <hi>March,</hi> the Treaty was concluded ratified, and executed before the end of <hi>Iune.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Gordian knot, which was thought would have required the ſword of <hi>Alexander</hi> to cut, before it could be undone, was tied in this manner. In the time of <hi>Charles le bon</hi> grandfather to the preſent Duke of <hi>Savoy, Charles</hi> the fift, and <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt warring one againſt the other, did <hi>par droict de bien ieame,</hi> ſhare and divide betwixt themſelves almoſt all <hi>Pied-mont,</hi> ſo that little being left unto the good Duke <hi>Charls,</hi> but <hi>Savoy</hi> and the Countey of <hi>Niſla</hi> in Province, he was inforced for the ſupply of his urgent neceſſities to borrow a conſiderable ſum of money of the Sſ<hi rend="sup">ri</hi>. of <hi>Berne,</hi> unto whom he did impawn for their reimburſment the Countrey of <hi>Vaud.</hi> After his death his ſon <hi>Emanuel Philibert</hi> having little to maintain himſelf at home, did adhere
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119672:20"/>unto <hi>Philp</hi> the ſecond, of whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſo wel in the Battle of S. <hi>Quintin,</hi> that the King was content to reſtore unto him that he did hold of his in <hi>Pied-mont,</hi> and becauſe he married the Lady <hi>Margarite de Valois</hi> daughter of <hi>France,</hi> in contemplation of her. <hi>Henry</hi> the third paſſing through <hi>Pied-mont,</hi> as he returned out of <hi>Polonia,</hi> reſtored unto him likewiſe all that the French had uſurped: yet was not this Prince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, with this addition to his fortune to redeem the ingagement of the <hi>pais de Vaud,</hi> and being willing to enjoy quietly that which he had, he did confirm un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Berneſi, the morgage made by his father, ſo that they did live in peace during his time, though not without great jealouſies, in regard of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Savoyards their confining neighbours, who had alwayes had them in deteſtation ſince the morgage of that Province.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> now regnant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born under a Martial Planet, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>ſagittarius aſcendant</hi> in his nativity, did affright the Berneſi at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and not long after it did appear that they did not fear him in vain, for he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119672:20"/>did preſently caſt his eye upon the <hi>Pais de Vaud,</hi> and becauſe he could not abruptly break the contract of Morgage made by his Granfather, and ratified by his father, and was not able to pay the principal and intereſt, which in ſo many years was grown to a great ſum, he did lay his firſt claim to the Town of <hi>Geneva,</hi> in the defence of which Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Berneſi being ingaged, they were of neceſſity to declare themſelves his enemies, and ſo miniſter unto him a fit occaſion of invading them, which was the thing that he did aime at, and he had fortune ſo favourable, that in the year 83. as I take it, he did ſhut them up ſo cloſe in <hi>Cologne,</hi> a Town three miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from <hi>Geneva,</hi> near the <hi>Roſne,</hi> that they were inforced to yeeld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his diſcretion. If falſe friends had ſeconded his true valour, it would have gone hard with <hi>Geneva</hi> and <hi>Berne</hi> both at that time. But the Spaniards upon whom he did wholy rely, at that time deſiring onely to imbroyl and conſume him a <hi>petit feu,</hi> and not to make any addition unto his fortune, did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him from proſecuting that deſigne, and turn him with his Army upon the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119672:21"/>conqueſt of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> during the combuſtions of the league in <hi>France.</hi> After he had wearied himſelf there, they did animate him to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Marquiſate of <hi>Salulles,</hi> which did ſucceed to his advantage in <hi>Italy,</hi> but to his loſſe on the other ſide of the hills, drawing upon him the victorious arms of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who did inforce him to exchange <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulles</hi> with the Bailliages of <hi>Breſſe, Baugó Verommè</hi> and <hi>Gez,</hi> which were the beſt flowers in the garden of <hi>Savoy.</hi> Now were the Berneſi out of danger, thoſe confining Provinces being out of his hands, and their ſtate in the protection of the French King, whom they had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſiſted during his troubles, both with men and money: yet did their jealouſies ſtill continue, until the invaſion of <hi>Monferrat Anno</hi> 1613. did draw upon the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> the arms of the king of <hi>Spain,</hi> which did enter into <hi>Pied-ment</hi> firſt <hi>Anno</hi> 1615. under the conduct of <hi>Don Gio: di Mendoza</hi> Marquis of <hi>Hyntioza,</hi> and ſecondly <hi>Anno</hi> 1617. under the command of <hi>Don Pedro di Toledo:</hi> it was time now for the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to ſeek for help from all places, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119672:21"/>therefore deſpairing of ever recovering the <hi>pais de Vaud,</hi> he was contented to give over a loſt game, upon condition that he might get ſome reaſonable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, for his reſignation. Here is the knot which I mentioned, for he did pretend much, and the Berneſi would not give any thing, alledging that they would not buy that which was their own already. Towards the untying of this knot, the authority of his Majeſty was uſed, the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> imploring, and the Berneſi accepting of his medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: means was found to reconcile theſe contradictions, with mutual ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, for the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> did receive as much as he could with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon expect, and yet the Berneſi did not ſtipulate with him for any thing; the expedient taken was this. The Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſi were deſired to concur with his Majeſtie in the aſſiſtance of the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> againſt the violence and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Spaniards, and in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof his Majeſtie did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and undertake to give them a final and total reſignation of the <hi>Pais de Vaud,</hi> free from any future claim or pretention. To gratifie his Majeſtie,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119672:22"/>the Berneſi did ſend unto the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> four thouſand men payed by them for three moneths, and in requital of this favour Sir <hi>Iſaac Wake</hi> did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto them two formal Acts, the one of the Duke, and the other of the Prince of <hi>Pied-mont,</hi> which did contain an abſolute ceſſion of all future claims or pretentions by any of that houſe to the <hi>pais de Vaud.</hi> This point being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated the treaty of Alliance was inſtantly concluded, but neither in the preface nor in the Articles was there any mention made of the ſuccours ſent by the Berneſi, or of the reſignation of the <hi>pais de Vaud,</hi> it being an Act paſſed meerly by his Majeſtie without any mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſtipulation of the parties, and as the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Pied-mont</hi> did truſt Sir <hi>Iſaac Wake</hi> with their Reſignations, ſo did the Berneſi give likewiſe unto him four thouſand men to diſpoſe of, as his Majeſtie ſhould be pleaſed to command, and ſo all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences were accommodated with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal contentment of both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and with much honour to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, who had no partner in this work, but the God of peace, whom he did
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119672:22"/>truly ſerve, and who did bleſſe his pious intentions. I have the more willingly ſpecified theſe particularities, becauſe the difficulties ſuppoſed to be inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſerve to illuſtrate the honour of my gracious Maſter, whoſe glorious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory I ſhall deſire may be perpetuated unto eternity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Miſunderſtandings and jealouſies.</head>
                     <p>Having ſhewed the ſtrength of that State which doth conſiſt in the bond of union, and confederation among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and Allyance with forein Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I muſt now point out ſome ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes of miſunderſtandings and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, which do indicate the weakneſs of that body, and threaten danger of the diſſolution thereof in time.</p>
                     <p>The firſt, like original ſin, is derived from the birth, and firſt conception of their liberty, which hath drawn upon them, and upon their poſterity an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary ill talent of the houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> who remembring very well that in former times they were ſoveraign lords of all that province, will never forget the wrong which they do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119672:23"/>hath been done unto them, by thoſe who under the pretext of vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating their lives and honour from the oppreſſion of tyrannical officers and Governours, have infranchiſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and caſt off the yoke of ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they owe unto the Arch Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> their natural Prince and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign. This will never he forgotten, but <hi>manet alta mente repoſtum,</hi> and when the Auſtriaci ſhall have power anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to their will, they will call theſe people to account, and like rivers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by force, ſeek to break away and enter into their firſt and original channel. <hi>Berne</hi> and <hi>Friburg</hi> may ſeem to pretend a little exemption from this general contagion of that body, in regard that they were infran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed from their firſt foundation, by the Duke of <hi>Ziringa</hi> their founder, and the name of the latter doth imply. If this were granted, that freedom muſt be confined within the walls of thoſe Towns, &amp; cannot be extended unto the inlargement of their dominion, wherein they have more then any one Canton, of what did anciently belong unto the Auſtriaci, and the Berneſi have a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119672:23"/>mark of greater envie then all the reſt, in regard that they are maſters at this day of the Caſtle of <hi>Habſburg,</hi> which was the patrimony of <hi>Rodolphe</hi> the firſt Emperour of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly the neighbourhood of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the vicinity of the French Countrey of <hi>Burgandis,</hi> is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorn in the ſide of that body; although <hi>Spain</hi> of it ſelf doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any thing that way, yet being head of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> family, they have a principal intereſt in al that doth belong unto that houſe, and if that were not ſo (as is too evident) yet the natural inclination and genius which that nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath, <hi>dilatare fines imperij,</hi> doth draw upon them an envious reputation of being ill neigbours, beſides that the greatneſſe of that Monarchy doth bring it within the compaſſe of the Italian proverb, which doth forbid a man to dwell neer four F. namely, <hi>Frati, Fiumi, Forni and Forti,</hi> and by conſequence greatly injealous all the Swiſſes, who have the laſt F. at their door. Beſides, as Duke of <hi>Milan,</hi> &amp; the king of <hi>Spain</hi> have a mortal quarel unto al the Cantons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119672:24"/>
                        <hi>Apenſelle,</hi> for their having uſurped (as he doth alledge) the Bailliages of <hi>Lugano, Madriſe, Lucarne, and Belinlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> which wre members of the Dutchey of <hi>Milan.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe are the main jealouſies, with which that whole body is troubled, and indeed all that I can remember, the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> being not to be ſpoken of in this place, in regard that <hi>Geneva</hi> is not numbered among the Cantons.</p>
                     <p>The particular miſunderſtandings are ſo much the more to be fear'd, as internal miſchiefes are more dangerous then external; they are many, and have ſeveral branches, but may be reduced all unto one head, and that is an alienation of affections, hatred and rancor cauſed by their diviſion, in matter of religion. This fatal diſtraction hath bred a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal faction, in which moſt of the Princes of Chriſtendom have part, the <hi>Pope,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and <hi>Spain</hi> openly fomenting, <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy</hi> favouring the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick party, and all the reformed Princes and States, wiſhing well unto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſide. Theſe latter have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motive but pure zeal, and a deſire of the preſervation of that true religion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119672:24"/>whereof they do make profeſſion, the orthodox Helvetians being a principal member of the reformed Church, and having like a Seminary produced men of extraotdinary learning and zeal, who have laboured in the vineyard of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, with much paines and great profit to the Church, ſuch as were <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inglius, Oecolampdius, Simler, Hoſpinian, Waſer,</hi> and many others who for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of ſouls, do now ſhine in heaven, like ſtars in the firmament. Thoſe who do foment the Catholicks, have divers ends, for although it may be preſumed that the <hi>Pope</hi> doth intend nothing but the reduction of that whole body to the obedience of the ſea of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein likewiſe there is ſo much mixture of worldly reſpect, as the increaſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Faires and Markets, do fill his coffers by the vent of his indulgences and pardons, yet it is certain, that the Emperour and the King of <hi>Spain</hi> have <hi>ragione di ſtato,</hi> which doth move them to adhere and take part with the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cantons. For beſides that thoſe diviſions and factions, are like the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Samſons</hi> locks, the ſtrength of that body conſiſting in union, as his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119672:25"/>did in his hair, if at any time they can prevail ſo far, as to kindle a war in thoſe parts grounded upon religion, they will ſoon make an end of the quarrel, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon both, parties when they have weakened one another; this deſigne is ſo well grounded, that it may perhaps rake effect in time, for ſince the reception of the Jeſuits in <hi>Iucerne</hi> and <hi>Friburg,</hi> exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerbations have daily increaſed, and nothing but the fear of a foreign enemy doth keep them now from a civil war. From this original fountain of habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al diſſention, grounded upon difference in religion, are derived many ſmal ſtreams of diſcord, which inereaſing the miſunderſtandings of thoſe people, are with much artifice cultivated by thoſe who for ſpiritual or temporal reſpects, deſire to trouble thoſe waters: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not particularize in all, becauſe ever and anon the Catholicks do make by the inſtigation of their partiſans, and their own natural inclination, <hi>une querelle d' Allemande,</hi> againſt the Proteſtants in which they do get nothing, becauſe they do meet with men that do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand reaſon, &amp; will not be out braved, but I will point at three iſſues which I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119672:25"/>have obſerved in that body, that do run perpetually, and will hardly be ſtopped, depending all of them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt head of diviſion in matter of Religion.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is a difference betwixt <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> and <hi>Friburg,</hi> who have four Baillia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in common, which they do govern alternatively in this manner, that when <hi>Berne</hi> doth name the Magiſtrate, he is bound to take his oath at <hi>Friburg,</hi> and when <hi>Friburg</hi> doth nominate him, he is to do the like at <hi>Berne,</hi> The names of theſe Bailliages, are <hi>Murate, Granſone, ſwarſbourg,</hi> and <hi>Eſhallons,</hi> and by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Acts of convention betwixt the two Towns it hath been ſtipulated long ſince, that for the preventing of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding betwixt them, their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of thoſe common Baillages ſhould be left at liberty, to exerciſe what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they liſted, with this proviſo, that when any of the communalties ſhould require <hi>le plus</hi> (which is as much as putting the queſtion) it ſhould be granted, and if the Catholick party had moſt voices, then no Religion ſhould be exerciſed in that juriſdiction, but the Roman, if the Proteſtants were ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerary
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119672:26"/>then the Catholicks were to yeeld. It hath ſo fallen out that the Preachers of the Goſpel having got the ſtart of the Prieſts and Friars, <hi>le plus,</hi> hath been demanded ſome years ſince by all thoſe four Bailliages, and the voices being all in advantage of the reformed religion, Popery hath been utterly exterminated. <hi>Friburg</hi> which hath equal juriſdiction alternatively, cannot endnre this innovation, and the Jeſuits who are potent in that Town have counſelled a diviſion of thoſe four Bailliages, that two may be for <hi>Berne</hi> intirely to diſpoſe of as they will, and the other two be left free for <hi>Friburg.</hi> The Berneſi will not hearken to this motion, but to hold themſelves ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto their capitulation, wiſely fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing, that if they ſhould come to a diviſion, the Friburgheſi would drive out the Proteſtants out of thoſe two Bailliages, which would touch unto them, and replant the Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond is a diſpute betwixt <hi>Zurick:</hi> and the little Cantons about the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Torgaw,</hi> which being morgaged ſome years ſince to <hi>Zurick,</hi> and not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119672:26"/>redeemed, poſſeſſion was taken, the <hi>Zurigani</hi> acknowledged for ſoveraigns, and the whole Countey reformed and made orthodox. The little Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons inſtigated by the Nontio and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, do except againſt the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and becauſe that cannot be altered as long as <hi>Torgaw</hi> is ſubject to <hi>Zurick,</hi> they do offer to repay the money, which the Zurigani will not accept, as well knowing that the point of religion is onely aimed at.</p>
                     <p>The third and laſt which I will note, is a controverſy betwix <hi>Glaris</hi> and <hi>Swits,</hi> about a Bailliage in common betwixt them both. For the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this puntilio, it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the Cantons of <hi>Glaris</hi> is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>party, half of the reformed religion, and the reſt Catholicks, but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have in all aſſemblies of that Canton, more then two thirds of their favour. Betwixt the Canton of <hi>Glaris</hi> and <hi>Switz</hi> by the Capitulations and Charters it is agreed, that in that Bailli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age common betwixt them both, alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natively each Canton ſhould depute their Bailiff. In vertue of this capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both the Cantons have alternative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119672:27"/>named their Bailiffs, and I think that <hi>Glaris</hi> being miſ-party did uſually name one of their body that was a Catholick, when it appertained unto them to nominate, but it is certain that they have of late choſen one of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, againſt whom thoſe of <hi>Switz</hi> have excepted, onely for being of the religion.</p>
                     <p>Theſe three controverſies are ſtill kept on foot by the Roman and Auſtrian par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and as they are alwayes debated at the general Dyett, held at <hi>Baden</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the nativity of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> ſo they alwayes part without reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any thing upon theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the form of Govenrment.</head>
                     <p>The name of a Republick doth imply an union, and that hath reference to an unity which is the beginning of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; for the delineating of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, we muſt of neceſſity have recourſe <hi>ad quantitatem diſcretam,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not <hi>continua,</hi> the body of their union, and unity of their body conſiſting in an accumulation or aggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119672:27"/>of thirteen Republicks diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in form of government, but joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a formal aſſociation among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the preſervation of their publike liberty. The ſeveral lines drawn from thirteen particular and diſtant ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies, and meeting all in one center of publick aſſociation; do make a ſhew of uniformity, and of this body <hi>Zurich</hi> is the viſible and figurative head, all letters written from foreign Princes or States, or from any of the particular Cantons which do require communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the Helvetian body, being to be preſented firſt unto the Borgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters of that Canton, who have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to open them, and to call a publick Dyett at <hi>Baden,</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of all ſuch letters, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning of anſwers as occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. They have no publick laws which do bend their whole body in matter of government, every Canton gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it ſelf by conſtitutions of their own framed ſutable and proportionable to the Ariſtocratical ſtate of ſome, and Democratical of others. Yet their <hi>Magna Carta,</hi> or Charter of aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath ſome ſhew of a fundamental
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119672:28"/>Law, for that doth not onely combine them together in their league of mutual defence, but binde them likewiſe to ſtand to the deciſion of the major part, in all caſes which concern the integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their body, ſuch as are the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tnig or not, of any new Town or ſtate into the aſſociation of their common body, the renewing or diſſolving ſuch leagues as the whole body hath with fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princesorſtates, as namely with the houſe of <hi>Auſtria, France, Griſons,</hi> and <hi>Valeſani,</hi> the granting or denying lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies required by any confederate Prince of all the Cantons, the paſſage and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of foreign Armies or forces through their State, and the like. In all which caſes a Diet is to be called at <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and there the plurality of voices is to decide the cauſe, every Canton ſending thither two Ambaſſadours, or Deputies, whoſe firſt commiſsion is onely <hi>ad referendum,</hi> and when they have acquainted their ſeveral Maſters with what hath been propoſed, then doth every Canton ſend unto their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties their reſolution, yea or no, and according to the plurality of voices the queſtion is detemined. Some other
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119672:28"/>conſtitutions there are, which although they be not enacted by publick decree, yet are they religiouſly obſerved by every ſeveral Canton, and thoſe do concern leagues, which not the whole body, but any private Canton or Cantons do contract, with any fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince or State, wherein there are ſome Articles which do run in form, and are called Helvetical Cuſtoms. I will note ſome few, becauſe I cannot take notice of all. 1. All their leagues are meerly defenſive for the conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all their Allies, but not to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his enemy by way of invaſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their friend or neutral. 2. That Regiments be kept intire, and quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, not lodging one compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in one place, and another in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 3. That juſtice be adminiſtred by their own officers without appeal to the Prince or State whom their ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers do ſerve. 4. That their men be not commanded to go to any aſſault, but onely to guard Towns or trenches, or to fight in battle, in which laſt caſe, if the day prove theirs, they are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a moneths pay extraordinary. 5. and laſtly, They may not be made
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119672:29"/>to ſerve by ſea, either upon ſhips or gallies. They have no publick ſtock or treaſury, or any common Arſenac or Magazin of armes, but as every Canton is provided ſeverally, ſo in caſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion they are to ſend a proportion of men paied and furniſhed with ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of war and victuals. When they do make an offenſive war (which is not uſual) then ſuch Cantons as do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur therein, are to have part in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, proportionable to what they do contribute. At <hi>Baden</hi> they have a kind of <hi>Chambere de Contis,</hi> and every yeer at the feaſt of Saint <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> their Bailiffs, which do alternatively ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter and govern thoſe Bailliages which are in common, do there give up their accounts, which are reſerved and kept in Archives there. If any foreign Prince do call a publick Diet at <hi>Baden,</hi> to propoſe any thing, his Ambaſſadour muſt defray all the Deputics that meet there upon that occaſion, during the time of that aſſembly, one of the Borgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of <hi>Zurich</hi> being alwayes ſpeaker or prolocutor in thoſe Diets, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning the anſwer to the Ambaſſador in the name of all the reſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119672:29"/>
                     <head>Confederate Neighbours.</head>
                     <head type="sub">GRISONS.</head>
                     <p>MY relation being confined to <hi>Helvetia,</hi> I will ſpeak of their neighbours no more then what doth concern their relation unto the <hi>Helve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> body. The Griſons are the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temurali</hi> of <hi>Helvetia,</hi> towards the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Tirol,</hi> and with them beſides the <hi>ligue de regarde</hi> which all the Cantons have with the three leagues of the Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, called the <hi>Griſa, là di Dio, &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eci Dritture,</hi> the proteſtant Cantons have in general an Alliance of defenſive combination, and the two Cantons of <hi>Zurick</hi> and <hi>Berne</hi> a More ſpecifical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation tending to the defence of that Republick. The Biſhop of <hi>Coir</hi> is a perpetual <hi>lapis ſcandali,</hi> for he doth pretend to be ſupreme Prince of that ſtate as well in <hi>temporalibus as in ſbiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alibus,</hi> and whoſoever doth reſide in that ſea, is fomented by the Auſtriaci, incouraged by the Popes Nuntio reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at <hi>Lucerne</hi> in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> and favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119672:30"/>by the Catholick Cantons. The Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold</hi> did aſpire many years to that Biſhoprick, and there is nothing more feared in thoſe parts, then that one day ſome Prince of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> may get the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of that Church. The <hi>Griſons</hi> do not pretend <hi>jus nominandi,</hi> which is free to the Canons of the Church, and cannot be taken from them, but they have ſo tied the hands of former Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops with capitulations, that the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral govenrment doth remain in the hands of the three leagues, and the Biſhop hath nothing left him but the name.</p>
                     <p>Theſe people were for a long time wholy devoted to the ſervice of the French Crown, and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth did not onely much eſteem of their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, but carefully watch over the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of that Republick; for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity whereof, he employed his potent offices to joyn them in league with the Venetians; but that league expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring within a few years after his death, the French Miniſters did ſo much ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect and contemn that nation, that the Auſtriaci and Spaniards had the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119672:30"/>opportunity, firſt to raiſe a party or facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with whom they did treat Alliance, and afterwards to ſeiſe themſelves by force, of <hi>Rhoetia</hi> and the <hi>Valtelina,</hi> from whence did ſpring all thoſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and innovations that have been in thoſe parts, ſince the year 1617. until the preſent, at which time having been worſe cured by the Phyſitians of <hi>France Venice</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> then they had been wounded by their enemies, they do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy but a ſhadow of liberty, and do incline again to treat Alliance with <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>San Gallo.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>San Gallo</hi> bordering upon <hi>Glaris,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſeil</hi> doth confine with <hi>Suevia,</hi> toward the lake of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> This town is popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, rich, of great trade, and is in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wholy orthodox and reformed. The Abbot doth claim ſoveraignty, and ſtile himſelf Prince, governing abſolutely throughout all that juriſdiction, except the town, which having infranchiſed it ſelf, and excluded him, doth live free under protection of the Cantons, who do carefully invigilate upon the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119672:31"/>of that place, as being a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal bulwark of defence unto them from any invaſion which may be atemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Auſtriaci, by the way of <hi>Suevia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Milhuſen.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Milhuſen</hi> confining with the Rauraci towards <hi>Alſatia,</hi> is the beſt defence the Swiſſes have that way, and the onely guard of the town of <hi>Baſil.</hi> The Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold</hi> doth look with an envious eye upon the liberty ſpiritual and temporal, which they do enjoy under the protection of the Swiſſes, and theſe are very jealous of their preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, eſpecially the Proteſtant Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, who are <hi>paries proximus,</hi> and unto whom the Auſtriaci in general, and the Arch-Duke in particular doth bear a very ill talent. They have often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted upon fortifying that Town, which would quickly be made very defenſible, but the Citizens being poor and not able, and the Swiſſes covetous and not willing to diſburſe any money, it hath hitherto been neglected, and may in time indanger their ruin.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119672:31"/>
                     <head>Valeſani.</head>
                     <p>This Republick doth conſiſt of ſeven <hi>Ditains</hi> or Tithings, every <hi>Ditain</hi> being an aggregation of ten Pariſhes. Their form of government is Democratical, &amp; al the people have a deliberatire voice in the election of officers, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining of publick affaires. The Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff (who is the repreſentative head of that Common-wealth) and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers his aſſiſtants, do alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in <hi>Lion</hi> the Metropolis of that State, and from thence they ſend to the ſeveral <hi>Ditanis</hi> for their votes, upon all important occaſions. They have a perpetual quarrel with the Biſhop of that ſea, who doth claim Monarchical ſoveraignty, which it ſhould ſeem his predeceſſors have in former times either uſurped or enjoyed, if not abſolutely (which I will not deſide) yet in a very great latitude, as may appear by the Cardinal Biſhop of <hi>Lion,</hi> who not a hundred yeers ſince, did bring into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> an army of thirty thouſand men, for the ſervice of the Pope. This could not be done without much authority, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119672:32"/>great revenue, which is ſo much dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at this preſent, that the Biſhops of latter yeers have ſcarce wherewithall to maintain <hi>honeſtam familiam, &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem cum decoro;</hi> yet do they ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſtrongly to the recovery of what they do conceive hath been unjuſtly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them, but the Magiſtrate doth ſo clip their wings, that they cannot fly very high, wherein that Republick hath this advantage, that no religion being profeſſed there publickly but the Roman, (although there be among them a great number of orthodox) the Biſhop cannot make it a queſtion of religion, and by conſequence doth want that open protection of the Pope, Emperour, <hi>Spain,</hi> and Catholick Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, which is upon all occaſions offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Biſhops of <hi>Coir, Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> whoſe caſe is all alike, ſetting religion aſide. This Repubilck hath a defenſive league with the whole body of the Cantons, and likewiſe with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> but with State of <hi>Berne,</hi> they have a more ſtrict confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in regard of the vicinity of both thoſe States.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119672:32"/>
                     <head>Neufchaſtel.</head>
                     <p>This County ſeated upon the border of a lake which doth take his name from the Town, is ſubject unto the Duke of <hi>Longueville,</hi> who is lord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſo acknowledged: yet is not his ſoveraignty abſolute, but reſtrained with immunities, &amp; priviledges which he cannot infringe or innovate: The inhabitants do enjoy <hi>le droict de com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgoiſie</hi> with the Town of <hi>Berne,</hi> and in caſe of difference betwixt the Prince and ſubject, the lords of <hi>Berne</hi> are to decide the queſtion. This is a great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification of Monarchical ſupremacy, in regard that appeals are never made, but to a higher power. They being all Proteſtants, the Duke hath often attempted to reduce then to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man religion, but they have ſtill ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved themſelves by appealing to the Berneſi, by whom they are ſo potently protected, that when he did few yeers ſince tranſport himſelf in perſon to <hi>Neufchaſtel,</hi> and carry a prieſt with him to ſay Maſſe in the Caſtle, he was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in oppoſed, although it was his own
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119672:33"/>houſe. The Duke is protected by the French King who hath often threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to aſſiſt the Duke with a potent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but hitherto he hath forborn the execution of that violent deſigne, for fear, not onely of the Berneſi, who are very potent, but of the Spaniards like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, who will not ſuffer the French to be abſolute Maſters of a province which doth confine with the County of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Bienne.</head>
                     <p>This Town ſeated upon a branch of the lake of <hi>Newfchaſtel,</hi> is a little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick allied <hi>with Berne</hi> by <hi>combour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goiſie.</hi> They are all of the religion, and not troubled with any pretenders to their liberty ſpiritual or temporal, but do live ſecurely under the protection of <hi>Berne,</hi> and do enjoy all the liberties of that Town as free deniſons; ſerving joyntly unto that State as a good ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murale againſt the French County of <hi>Burgandy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119672:33"/>
                     <head>Geneva</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Geneva</hi> doth ſtand in the bottom of a lake, unto which it doth give name. The river of <hi>Rhoſne</hi> doth run through part of the city on the one ſide, and the river <hi>Arva</hi> doth paſſe by it on the other ſide. This Republick was received into the protection and confederation with the Canton of <hi>Berne</hi> in the yeer 1592. or there abouts, and doth ſerve as a ſtrong bulwark to ſecure the Berneſi from any invaſion that way. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> in the time of the league, did imploy his beſt offices to incantoniſe this Town, wiſely foreſeeing that in time <hi>Spain</hi> would overbalance <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> where he (being then a Proteſtant) could onely promiſe unto himſelf the devotion of four orthodox Cantons, and the two miſparties, and <hi>Spain</hi> was ſure of the other ſeven. Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of voices in the general Diet of <hi>Baden,</hi> doth overſway all buſineſſes, but equality doth make a ſtop, and inforce <hi>ſine temperamento.</hi> If he could have made <hi>Geneva</hi> a fourteenth Canton (as his purpoſe was) then the Pope, Emperour
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119672:34"/>and <hi>Span</hi> had loſt all hope of predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating there, which now they have with the odde voice: but ſince his death, the government of France hath fallen into the hands of miniſters, who do what they can to advantage the Spaniſh faction in thoſe parts, and to ſuppreſſe thoſe who were and are moſt devoted to the French Crown. Unto the ſoveraignty of this town the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> doth pretend in <hi>temporalibus,</hi> and the Biſhop <hi>in temporalibus &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualibus.</hi> The Town doth ſave it ſelf, like an <hi>Animal amphibion,</hi> as may be ſeen by their armes, which are the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle on the one ſide, and the keys on the other: with the keys, they do exclude the houſe of <hi>Savoy</hi> alledging that none can pretend there but the Biſhop, and with the eagle they do ſoar over the Biſhop, declaring that their City is imperial. If any man be curious to ſee the ſtate of this controverſie, let him read <hi>le Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal. Savoyſien,</hi> written by a Savoyard, and the anſwer thereunto, called <hi>le Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadin di Geneve,</hi> written by Mr, <hi>Saralin,</hi> though his name be not affixed: theſe are pamphlets of ſmall volume, which do ſtate that queſtion <hi>pro &amp; contra.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119672:34"/>Pere Monnau</hi> a Jeſuit confeſſour unto Madam <hi>Chreſtienne</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> hath likewiſe written a book in octavo in favour of the houſe of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> which was printed in <hi>Turin Anno</hi> 1622. but never publiſhed or divulged; a copy whereof Sir <hi>Iſaac Wake</hi> did ſend to <hi>Geneua,</hi> as ſoon as it did paſſe the preſſe, and if they be not provided of an anſwer, upon all occaſions, it is their fault. The ſituation of this Town doth ſecure it from danger, for it cannot be beſieged unleſſe armies do lodge and quarter within the dominions of <hi>France Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Berne,</hi> and that there be a fleet likewiſe to command the lake: if they be true within themſelves, I do conceive it to be the moſt impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place in all Europe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:119672:35"/>
                     <head>Of the uſe of correſpondence in thoſe parts, as far as it doth concern the Crown of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is a Maxime irrefragable, that when enemies or ill-willers do op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or maligne the proceedings of any Prince or State, they are to be eſteemed behoofful and advantagious for the Actors. From that Aphoriſme I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the correſpondence of his Majeſty in <hi>Helvetia</hi> and <hi>Rhetia</hi> is not onely good but neceſſary, having found by expecting that the Pope, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> have expreſſed diſpleaſure at the appearing of any Miniſter of his Majeſties in thoſe parts, upon whatſoever occaſion.</p>
                     <p>Extention and latitude of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence doth adde unto the honour of great Princes, and moſt commonly conduce to their ſervice, as was well known &amp; obſerved by the wiſe <hi>Cardenal
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119672:35"/>Wolſey,</hi> who left no Prince nor little State of Chriſtendom without an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour or Agent of his maſter. The Venetians do obſerve the ſame ſtile, and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh who did hate foreign Ambſſadours in his own Court, was frequent in employing his own a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</p>
                     <p>If it be ſaid that we have no need of them, it may be anſwered, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſometimes they may have need of us, and being fellow-members of the body of our Religion, do deſerve not onely countenance but protection. The Proteſtants in thoſe parts are often braved by their Allayes of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cantons, who being fomented by the Popiſh and Auſtriacal party do inſult upon them many times, Contentions and diſputes do ariſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and the poor and ſimpler ſort of people intimidated with the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo potent enemies; do unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly concur with the Magiſtrates in the defence of their liberty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in ſuch caſes (which are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent there) the ſight of a miniſter of ſo great a Monarch as is his Majeſtie, wil invigorates the moſt ſtupid among them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119672:36"/>and the opinion of his royall protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will incourage them to maintain a good cauſe.</p>
                     <p>The ſeat of that place is very proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to <hi>andamenti</hi> of thoſe upon whoſe proceedings it is fit that wealwayes have a vigilant eye, for from thence as from a watch-tower we may eaſily diſcover long before whatſoever they do intend.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe people are not onely auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, of which moſt princes doth ſerve themſelves, eſpecially <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> who do buy the love of the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons at a dear rate, that they may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with men, when they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any: in which regard it will be fit that his Majeſty were alwayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed aforehand when any leavy is intended to be made in thoſe parts, that knowing what innovation is machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by any of thoſe Princes who do require auxilliaries, he may govern himſelf accordingly as the ſtate of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires ſhall miniſter occaſion.</p>
                     <p>The paſſage out of <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Vice Verſa,</hi> is a point of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant conſideration, and as it may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port much to know when any paſſage is demanded, and by whom, ſo will it be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119672:36"/>eaſy for a careful miniſter, to diſcover afore-hand the deſigne of thoſe that ask the paſſage, and perhaps he may ſometimes have credit enough (upon ſome occaſions either to ſtop or delay the paſſage, if it may prove prejudicial to any friends of his Majeſties, or to faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate it, if it may turn to their ſervice or advantage.</p>
                     <p>The State of <hi>Venice</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> his Majeſties good friends, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Alliance with ſome of the Cantons, may have uſe of the power and credit of his Majeſty in thoſe parts: for as in the year 1615 the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Cantons, did upon a letter of his Majeſties of glorious memory, grant the paſſage through their dominions unto ſuch troups as the Count <hi>Iohn de Naſſaw</hi> had then raiſed for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> in deſpight of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and in the year 1618 the Berneſi at the requeſt of his foreſaid Majeſtie did lodge in the <hi>Pais de vaud</hi> and give quarter unto Count <hi>Mansfelts</hi> army (retyring then out of <hi>Pied-mont</hi>) four monthes together, untill <hi>Vorcelli</hi> was ſurrendered, ſo hereafter occaſions of the like nature
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119672:37"/>may preſent themſelves, wherein his Majeſty may favour his friends, with his authority and good offices.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, it is to be preſumed that the Palatinate and Marquiſate of <hi>Baden</hi> ſhall be reſtored in due time, and in that caſe the neigborhood of the four Evangelical cities, who have Alliance with <hi>Straſbourg,</hi> may prove of good conſideration, and a Miniſter of his Majeſties will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to cement the intelligence and good correſpondence which may be renewed betwixt thoſe Princes and the foreſaid Cantons.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119672:37"/>
                     <head>Of the name and Original of the <hi>Helvetij</hi> hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically.</head>
                     <p>MAny nations do ſeek their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree further then it can be found: and ſome of them are ſorry to finde what they did ſeek. <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid quaeritur, optimum videtur:</hi> yet a modeſt ignorance is in many caſes more comfortable, then any vain curioſity can profit. The Arcadians did flee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the moon, and call themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. The Helvetians (like their Antipodes) go under ground and paſſe the center of the earth to ſeek their original. They are not aſhamed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their extraction <hi>a Dite inferorum Deo,</hi> and their name hath conſonancy with their fantaſie, for <hi>Helvatter</hi> in their language is the father of Hell, and anciently they were called <hi>Helvetteri qnaſi inferno nati,</hi> which name the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans with the advantage of a more
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119672:38"/>eaſy pronuntiation, did corrupt into <hi>Helvetij.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This etymologie of the name will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be accepted by thoſe who will give credit to <hi>Aegidius Tſchudus,</hi> and <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Glareanus,</hi> who do affirm that the ancient Gauls did ſpeak the German tongue, and eſpecially that of the Helvetij, for although I will not affirm the uniformity of their language, yet this conceit <hi>de Dite Patre</hi> either was infuſed to the Gauls by the Helvetians, or common to them both as one people; for <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> doth write of the Gauls in this manner, <hi>Omnes ſe ab Dite Patre prognatos praedicabant, id<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> â Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idibus proditum dicebant.</hi> This name an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently formidable to the Romans, was in a manner extinguſhed when <hi>Aulus Caecinna</hi> did overcome and beat them <hi>aplate couſture ad Vindoniſſam,</hi> which was ſo perfect a conqueſt, that he did divide the whole Country into two Provinces, <hi>Sequance</hi> and <hi>Rhaetia.</hi> After that conqueſt, they did look more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Germany</hi> then towards the Gauls, and in time did wholy paſſe into the name, manners, cuſtoms, and tongue of the Germans; when being impatient
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119672:38"/>of their ſubjection to the Romans, the inhabitants did joyn with the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, to deliver themſelves of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond name and moſt known of that Country at this day is <hi>Saitia</hi> Swiſſerland, but the etymologie is as uncertain as of the former, in regard of the variety of opinions; ſome (with the addition of the letter s. at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning would derive them <hi>à vitis</hi> a people of <hi>Saxony,</hi> whom <hi>Charles</hi> the great did drive out of their own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for frequent rebellions, and confine. within the ſtraight paſſages of the Alpes, Others run into <hi>Sweden,</hi> and bring them from the Sueci, who in the time of king <hi>Sigebert</hi> made a tranſmigration out of Suecia, and planted themſelves in this Country.</p>
                     <p>A third opinion there is of ſome wiſe in their own conceit, who do bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe them Swiſſes, from a war which thoſe of <hi>Zurick</hi> did make eight years together in the time of <hi>Frederic</hi> the third againſt thoſe of <hi>Swits, Glaris,</hi> and their confederates. But we need not go ſo far, for it is moſt probable that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119672:39"/>the wholy Countrey did take this name from the village or now Canton of <hi>Swits</hi> where the firſt foundation of the Helveti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal league was layed, the fabrick where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was ſhortly after raiſed to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by a memorable victory which they gained not far from that village upon the Auſtriaci, who came with great forces to break their new begun confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
                     <p>So much of the name; as for their firſt plantation, they do pretend almoſt as high as the flood, for they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that <hi>Zurick</hi> and <hi>Soluere</hi> are coeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall with <hi>Triers,</hi> the firſt foundation whereof is thought to have been in the time of the Patriarch <hi>Abraham,</hi> almoſt two thouſand yeers before the birth of our Saviour; All the Annals of Helvetia are conſtant in this aſſertion, and I will rather beleeve them, them ſeek ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to confute them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the extention of Helvetia.</head>
                     <p>This Coutrey was anciently confined betwixt the mountains <hi>Iura,</hi> and <hi>lake</hi> of <hi>Geneva, Italy</hi> and the <hi>Rhine.</hi> Now <hi>Baſil, Schpahuſen,</hi> and <hi>Roteville,</hi> which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119672:39"/>
                        <hi>Iura,</hi> and the <hi>Rhine</hi> and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pontij, namely thoſe of <hi>Belinſona, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, Locarne</hi> and <hi>Madriſe,</hi> on the other ſide of the <hi>Alpes</hi> towards <hi>Italy,</hi> being incorporated into that body, have much increaſed the ancient limits thereof from the north towards the South.</p>
                     <p>The Gaeodectical longitude accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto <hi>Caeſars</hi> account, ſhould be 240. miles, and the latitude 180. Moſt of the later Geographers do agree with him in the longitude, but they do conceive that he did extend the latitude further then it did reach in his time and <hi>Glare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> (who doth excuſe <hi>Caeſar,</hi> by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he did take it upon truſt and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay) hath contracted it to the extenſion of three dayes journey. <hi>Ortelius</hi> to 160. miles, <hi>Iohn Henry Switlerus,</hi> to 100. <hi>Tſchudus</hi> and <hi>Mercator</hi> to 80. with theſe ſupputations, the journals do well agree, for from <hi>Geneva</hi> to <hi>Conſtance</hi> (which are the extremities of the length) they do account 48 leagues, and from <hi>Baſil</hi> to Saint <hi>Gotard</hi> (which is the bredth 20. one of thoſe leagues, being near about five Italian miles, the difference will not be great, betwixt the account of the former and of the latter.</p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119672:40"/>
                     <p>Theſe were the ancient bonnds of <hi>Helvetia,</hi> the breadth whereof (as I have noted) is now augmented ſince their paſſing the hills, and having ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto their dominion a good part of the Dutchy of Milan.</p>
                     <p>From hence the Coſmographical Longitude, and Latitude may eaſily be collected. For <hi>Como</hi> called <hi>Forum Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis</hi> with which they do now confine, being in the Latitude of 45 degrees and 6. Minuits, and <hi>Baſil</hi> in 47. and 30 the difference wilbe found to be of 2. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and 24. Minutes of Latitude, and will cut through the midſt of the ſixt Climet unto the beginning of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth. The difference of the Meridions, or of the Longitude, from <hi>Geneva</hi> unto Saint <hi>Gallo</hi> neer Conſtance, which is the greateſt Extenſion from the Weſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt, is about 3 degrees and 46 Minutes of the leſſer Circle if wee follow the Mappes, but being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Calculation of the Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, it doth contain 5 degrees, ſo that the whole Country is bounded and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiened, within the Meridians, 27.30. and 32.30.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119672:40"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119672:41"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119672:41"/>
                  <p>A DISCOVRSE OF THE State of <hi>ITALIE,</hi> as it ſtood about the year 1625. OR SOMEWHAT AFTER.</p>
                  <p>Directed to the late <hi>KING CHARLS</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Reign.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119672:42"/>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:119672:42"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Almightie God, To eſtabliſh your ſacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in the royal throne of your ever bleſſed Father, I have held it my duty, with bended heart and knee, to preſent unto your Majeſty at the beginning of your reign a ſhort view of the preſent eſtate and condition of <hi>Italy,</hi> that therein, as in a little Map, your Majeſtie may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119672:43"/>ſee the true face of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and make ſuch uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hereafter, as in your Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdom you ſhall finde to conduce moſt to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of your own affaires, Crowns, and dignities.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119672:43"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THE POPE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O begin with Rome, that ſeat is poſſeſſed at this preſent by <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> the eighth a Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine by extraction, of the family of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bireni,</hi> a Prince of of a vigorous age, active Spirit, great experience, who hitherto hath done little to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, nothing to be blamed. He did fall at the beginning of his reign into troubleſome times, for his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth did leave him a foſterchilde of the <hi>Valtelina,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any portion but charge, expence and trouble. This infant was ſurreptitiouſly taken out of the cradle by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, who being not able to keep it lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from the true father, the Griſons
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119672:44"/>in whoſe favour <hi>France, Venice,</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy</hi> did appear, did put it into the hands of the Church, as into a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary. In the election of Pope <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the French faction had the affirmative and active part, for it was the hand of the Cardinal of <hi>Savoy</hi> that did put that Crown upon his head; the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards had onely a paſſive and negative part, in not excluding him, which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour they do account to be great, and he doth eſteem to be ſomething. As ſoon as he was enthroned, he did finde his Crown to be full of thorns, for ſome of his promotors did pretend to all that he could give, and all unto ſomething; to pleaſe all, it was impoſſible, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe any, dangerous, until he had his houſe ſetled, and his friends about him. Being unwilling to diſoblige <hi>France</hi> and the league, and fearing to offend the Spaniards, he did reſolve at the firſt upon a neutrality, conceiving that, to ſute beſt with his quality of <hi>Padre commune,</hi> and hoping in time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive unto himſelf the honour of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodating thoſe differences by way of negotiation. But his expectation was deceived; for by this temporizing the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119672:44"/>
                        <hi>Valielina</hi> was loſt, not without ſome diſhonour to him, and ſo loſt, that he hath no thanks from the league, and many curſes from the Spaniards. This pill, although it were very bitter, he would have paſſed over, if it had wrought no further; but when the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the Conſtable <hi>d' Eſdignieris</hi> did begin to march into the field, the Spaniards did grow ſo clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that he was inforced to gratifie them in ſuch things as they did deſire, though perhaps that which he hath done will not turn to their advantage. The things which they did require, were, that he ſhould ſend his Nephew into <hi>France</hi> to procure a ſuſpenſion of armes, and that himſelf ſhould arm po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently within his dominions to joyn with them in the defence of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, and the liberty of <hi>Italy.</hi> Theſe requeſts have been granted, for his Nephew is not in <hi>France,</hi> and he hath raiſed, and given order for the raiſing of twelve thouſand foot &amp; two thouſand horſe; but what his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to do, is hard to gueſs. It is certain that if he do love the French and the league but a little, he doth fear
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119672:45"/>the Spaniards much, and therefore theſe armes of his may be as well to defend himſelf againſt them, as to offend any of the league, againſt whom he doth now profeſſe that he cannot declare himſelf, becauſe <hi>il ſuo. pegno, è in Francia;</hi> That he will imploy his armes againſt the league it is unlikely; for although he doth inherit one quality of all his Predeceſſors, which is to hate the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, yet he will fear to loſe by the bargain, conſidering that the beſt part of his dominions doth lie open to the Adriatick ſea, of which the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are abſolute maſters, and may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage all his country at their pleaſure. That he doth fear the Spaniards, there are ſome probabilities, as his with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing the Jubily from the Church of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſhutting up of that gate which doth lead towards <hi>Naples:</hi> his taking in and railing a garden belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the Conſtable <hi>Colonna,</hi> confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with <hi>Monte Cavallo,</hi> and ſeeming a little to command that palace, his having required the ſaid <hi>Colonna,</hi> (who is a Roman, but Conſtable of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Naples</hi> likewiſe) to deliver into his hands a Caſtle of his upon the confine
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119672:45"/>betwixt <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> and laſtly, his having commanded all Cardinals and Prelates of quality, to bring their unwrought and unguilded plate unto his exchequer, allowing them upon the Monti (which are certain banks of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in <hi>Rome</hi>) one hundred and twenty four Julij, (which is five pound twelve ſhillings ſterling) for every pound weight. Theſe are arguments that he doth fear ſome body, and whom he can fear, but the Spaniards, cannot be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined: for the kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> is at his doore: the French are too far off, the Duk of <hi>Savoy</hi> too weak of himſelf, and of the Venetians he is ſure that if they may live in peace, they will diſturb no body: ſome are ſo wiſe as to think, that ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he doth underſtand with <hi>France,</hi> and that he would willingly lay claim un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> if the league would bring the Spaniards ſo low, that he might dare to appear; but it doth plainly appear by his Miniſters abroad, and their negotiations in all places, that he doth really and diligently ſeek to divert the ſtorm which is threatened unto the Genoeſi, and by conſequence unto the Spaniards, whether it be that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119672:46"/>hope of good from them, or fear of hurt from innovations, or an ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be the arbitrator, doth move him none can tell but he who hath the key of hearts. It is likely that he would fain ſee an end of theſe troubles, becauſe being a Prieſt and a Florentine too, he hath no minde to ſpend, and although he hath not done yet much for any of his houſe, yet perhaps he would imitate his predeceſſors in that kinde, which he can hardly do untill this ſtorm be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blown.</p>
                     <p>Untill it ſhall appear what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of <hi>Genova</hi> and <hi>Breds,</hi> he will not unmaſk himſelf certainly: but it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that according to the event of thoſe two great enterpriſes, he may ſail as he ſhall finde the winde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:119672:46"/>
                     <head>The King of Spain.</head>
                     <p>THe dominions which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> doth poſſeſſe upon the Continent of <hi>Italy,</hi> are the kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Dutchy of <hi>Milan. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> doth afford him good ſtore of men, and ſome money. <hi>Milan</hi> ſome few men, but no money, with theſe two, they have long kept <hi>Italy</hi> in awe, rather by reputation then force: for they have not four thouſand Spaniards in both thoſe Provinces. The ſubjects have groaned a long time under a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie burden of miſgovernment, and if a fair occaſion ſhould be offered, it is thought they would willingly <hi>mutare dominum, non ſervitutem,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Naples:</hi> for though the carriage of the Duke of <hi>Feria</hi> hath been mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, yet he had ill fortune to fall into times, when the ſervice of his Maſter would not ſuffer him to eaſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects according to his deſire. The beſt flower in the garden of the Spaniſh
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119672:47"/>Monarchy is the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi> for that is the ſtomack from whence is derived the aliment which doth nouriſh all his ſtates in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> and the low Countries; that reſt is now at ſtake; for if the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the Conſtable do incounter at <hi>Genova,</hi> a check given there, doth mate <hi>Milan,</hi> and the cards are ſo well packt, that if they no not ſhuffle them anew at <hi>Paris,</hi> it will prove a hard game, and very dangerous for the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard. The vicinity of <hi>Helvetia,</hi> the proximity of <hi>Germany</hi> by the way of <hi>Tirol,</hi> the neerneſſe and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of <hi>Genova,</hi> did really make the ſtate of <hi>Milan</hi> formidable to all <hi>Italy,</hi> and terrible to all their neighbours. If <hi>Genova</hi> do now fall, all hope of mony is loſt, and no more Neapolitans, Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians nor Spaniards can enter into <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardy.</hi> The Swiſſes, when they ſhall ſee that <hi>Genova,</hi> from whence they had all their Spaniſh penſions, is no longer at the devotion of <hi>Spain,</hi> will quickly faint, and they have likewiſe a ſtrong counterpoiſe of the Proteſtant Cantons, which being declared for the league, do keep the Catholick Cantons in awe.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119672:47"/>As for <hi>Tirol</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> they are of no further conſideration, for ſo much as doth regard the State of <hi>Milan, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſic ſtantibus:</hi> for the paſſages, which the Marquis <hi>di Coruvies</hi> hath taken in <hi>Rhaetia</hi> and the <hi>Valtelina</hi> do exclude all Almans from entering that way into <hi>Italy,</hi> and there is no other way for them, (the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> being of the contrary ſide) but onely through the ſtate of <hi>Venice,</hi> or of <hi>Swiſſerland.</hi> The kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> is like old <hi>Rome, Venalis ſi emptorem invenerit,</hi> the firſt opportunity that ſhall preſent it ſelf, will make them prove true Neapolitans, falſe to their laſt maſter, and ready to betray any that ſhall ſucceed; of <hi>Sicilie, Sardinia, Majorche</hi> and <hi>Minorche,</hi> I ſay nothing, becauſe they are Iſlands divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the main, and like <hi>Pinaſſes</hi> muſt follow the fortune of theſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhips.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119672:48"/>
                     <head>Florence Parma Nodena Luca</head>
                     <p>OF theſe I will ſpeake together: be-becauſe although they are ſupreme in their ſeveral circumferences, yet all their lines do meet in one center of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to the Crown of <hi>Spain, Florence</hi> being bound to give four thouſand men for <hi>Sienna, Parma</hi> three thouſand for <hi>Piacenta, Modena</hi> two thouſand for Penſions, and <hi>Luca</hi> two thouſand for Protection; their obligations do run one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the defence of the State of <hi>Milan,</hi> but yet the Marquis of <hi>Hinioſa</hi> and <hi>Don Pedro di Toledo</hi> did ſerve themſelves of their forces offenſively againſt the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> in the laſt wars of <hi>Aſti</hi> and <hi>Vercelli,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Feria</hi> hath made bold to employ their troups at this time in favour of the <hi>Genoeſi,</hi> as hath appeared by their enſignes and Commanders taken at <hi>Ottaggio.</hi> This
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119672:48"/>may prove <hi>lapis ſcandali,</hi> and perhaps hereafter thoſe Princes and ſtates may be called to an account, by the French and Savoyards, for having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in a quarrel in which they had nothing to do. Heretofore <hi>Florence</hi> did proceed more warily as long as <hi>Coſmus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> lived, for his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Madam <hi>Chriſtienne</hi> of <hi>Loreign,</hi> a Woman of imcomparable wiſdom, did ſo temper that government, that <hi>Spain</hi> was ſerved in what was due, and yet <hi>France</hi> was obſerved with a decorum befitting the extraction of the French king out of that houſe, and the Crown wherewith the queen mother hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured their family. But <hi>Coſmus</hi> the young Prince who hath ſince ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, being governed by the Arch-Ducheſſe who is ſiſter to the Emperour, doth derive all the ſilver ſtreams of that ſtate unto the Auſtrian <hi>Mille,</hi> ſo that France is now wholy neglected, and onely <hi>Spain</hi> reſpected. <hi>Edward Farneſe</hi> Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> being likewiſe very young, is governed by his Uncle the Cardinal <hi>Farneſe,</hi> whoſe red hat being died in the Court of Rome muſt needs incline him to follow the Popes directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119672:49"/>and that houſe having likewiſe the Dutchies of <hi>Caſtro</hi> and <hi>Caprarola</hi> lying within the kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> it is not to be marvelled if they do worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſouth. But it may ſeem ſtrange that <hi>Ceſare di Eſte</hi> Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> whoſe eldeſt ſon Prince <hi>Alfonſo</hi> hath married <hi>Iſabella</hi> the infanta of <hi>Savoy,</hi> by whom he hath ten children, ſhould run ſo violently the other way. Herein there is a myſtery ful of cunning malice, and malicious cunning. For ſhorly after the death of Prince <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who died in <hi>Palermo</hi> the laſt Summer) a will of his was produced, wherein he did declare his ſiſter of <hi>Modena haredem ex Aſſe,</hi> and bequeath unto his eldeſt ſon the Principalities of <hi>Oneglia</hi> and <hi>Marro.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> in vertue of this will, did lay claime unto all that might be thought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain unto Prince <hi>Philibert,</hi> and being oppoſed by the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who did firſt firſt except againſt the will as not being authentical, in regard that it was onely drawn by a Notary, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſigned by Prince <hi>Philibert;</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly alledge, that the ſon had no power to make a will during the life
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119672:49"/>of his father, and laſtly that <hi>Oneglia</hi> and <hi>Maro</hi> had ben lately conferred upon the Prince by his father, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe reſervations of returning to the Ducal chamber of <hi>Savoy,</hi> in caſe the Prince <hi>Philibert</hi> ſhould die without lawful iſſue, the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with this refuſal, did flee off from <hi>Savoy,</hi> and caſt himſelf into the arms of <hi>Spain:</hi> whoſe invention it was to caſt that bone betwixt thoſe two houſes of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Modena,</hi> may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily appear by the rule of <hi>Cui bono.</hi> The father having fallen off from <hi>Savoy,</hi> his younger ſon Prince <hi>Luiggi di Eſte</hi> muſt needs fall off as ſoon as he could from the Venetians, whereupon as ſoon as they had entertained the <hi>Count de la Tour</hi> for their General, Prince <hi>Luiggi</hi> ſeeming to be offended there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, did ask leave to be gone, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken at his word by theſe Sri. who did not like that the father ſhould ſerve the Spaniards, and the ſon the league, he retired to <hi>Modena</hi> about two moneths ſince.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119672:50"/>
                     <head>Mantova.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FErdinand Gonlaga,</hi> Duke of <hi>Manto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> hath his houſe free from any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency by obligation, but as his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies with <hi>Savoy</hi> did firſt inforce him to ſeek the protection of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſo ſince by marrying a daughter of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> and the marriage of his ſiſter <hi>Eleonora</hi> with the Emperour, he hath eſpouſed a tacite but abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devotion to the ſervice of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> He is a Prince whoſe natural and intellectual parts are ſingular, &amp; his moral good, unfortunate in having no lawful iſſue; for if he &amp; his brother <hi>Don Vincenlo</hi> die without heires male, their Niece the princeſſe <hi>Maria,</hi> daughter unto the late Duke <hi>Franceſco</hi> and the <hi>Infanta Margarita</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> wil carry from their houſe the marquiſate of <hi>Montferrat,</hi> and a 100000. crowns revenue of <hi>Beni Allodiali</hi> upon the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tovan.</hi> His differences with <hi>Savoy</hi> will
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119672:50"/>never be reconciled, as long as the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards have the upper hand in <hi>Italy;</hi> for <hi>Beati Pacifici</hi> is not to be found in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Spaniſh Liturgie. But in theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent innovations he doth not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, for <hi>Montferret</hi> concentrating with <hi>Piemont,</hi> and <hi>Mantova</hi> being ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the dominions of <hi>Venice,</hi> he hath onely <hi>voluntatem liberam,</hi> but <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem ligatam,</hi> with the State of <hi>Venice</hi> he doth hold very good quarter, and they do reſpect him as <hi>figlivolo di S. Marco.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of <hi>Genova</hi> nothing ſhall be ſaid, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it may appear what will become of them; for as they are now, either they muſt ſtand by the ſtrength of <hi>Spain,</hi> or bury the reputation of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, in the ruins of their City and State.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Venice.</head>
                     <p>THe Venetians did lay the firſt ſtone of this great building, upon which all the preſent innovations in theſe parts are grounded: for they did wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119672:51"/>foreſee, and earneſtly remonſtrate unto the French king and the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the danger which the publick liberties would run, if the dayly uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations of the Spaniards and Auſtriaci were not timely prevented. Hereupon the league was concluded at <hi>Lions,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified at <hi>Paris,</hi> confirmed at <hi>Suſa,</hi> and executed firſt by the Marquis <hi>di Coru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veres</hi> in the <hi>Valteline,</hi> and ſince by the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the Conſtable <hi>d' Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diguiſere</hi> in the <hi>Genoeſate.</hi> Their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in this buſineſſe have been, and are ſtil mixed with a conſtant tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of generoſity, and warineſſe; for they do not ſpare to aſſiſt and favour all that are contrary unto the Auſtrian party, as doth appear by their aſſiſting the ſtates of the united Provinces, their contributing to <hi>Mansfelt,</hi> their ſending of men, mony and ammunition to the Marquis <hi>di Coevures,</hi> their entertaining the <hi>Count de la Tour,</hi> and their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſet upon the ſtate of <hi>Milan</hi> when the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſhall begin: and yet they do very cautelouſſy keep themſelves to the letter of the league, and therefore they will not take notice of <hi>Mansfelt</hi> until
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119672:51"/>he may come ſo neer the <hi>Valteline</hi> that it may appear he was entertained by them, onely for that end, nor have any part in the enterpriſe of <hi>Genova,</hi> although they do very well know, that the weakening of the contrary party in any place, doth conduce unto the end which they do aime at. Good <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgians</hi> do not deſcend unto <hi>Cauteries,</hi> but in caſes of extremity, &amp; it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed of the wiſdom of the ſtate of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> that they would never have diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the peace of <hi>Italy,</hi> if they might have lived ſecurely, without innovation. They are not ignorant, that the remedy is little leſſe dangerous then the diſeaſe, but the diſeaſe being upon the point to grow incurable, they were inforced to apply that remedy which onely could ſave them (as things did ſtand then) from preſent precipitating. Of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy there is no doubt to be made; for they do wel know, that as they were the firſt that did raiſe this ſtorm, ſo they ſhall be the laſt whom the contrary party will forgive, and they have a maxime in this ſtate, that <hi>Priti &amp; Spag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuoli non perdonano mai.</hi> The correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> and at
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119672:52"/>this preſent with Rome, are onely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal with ſuch Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon <hi>Spain,</hi> ceremonial: with the French king and the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> real, with all Princes and ſtates oppoſit to the houſe of Auſtria, cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. By ſea, in their own ſea, they are ſtrong. Upon <hi>Terra firma</hi> they have all their Cities well furniſhed, and for the defenſive, they are in good ſtate. How they ſtand in matter of treaſure is a ſecret, but certainly <hi>omnes vias pecuniae norunt,</hi> and they do ſpend as if they did not fear to want.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Duke of Savoy.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>CHarles Emmanuel</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> with the <hi>Infanta Caterina</hi> did eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe the intereſts of <hi>Spain,</hi> and he was truly conſtant in ſerving that Crown and obſerving that King, until <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond making his peace with <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth did out of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to himſelf exclude his ſon in law the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> as may be ſeen in the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119672:52"/>Treaty of <hi>Vervins.</hi> Then did <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth lay claim to the Marquiſate of <hi>Salulles,</hi> which <hi>Savoy</hi> had uſurped by the counſel of <hi>Spain,</hi> and did retain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hope of aſſiſtance which was ſecretly promiſed, but not performed, The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards had obtained their end, when by the taking of <hi>Salulles</hi> the French were driven quite out of <hi>Italy;</hi> but becauſe they did not deſire that the houſe of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſhould aggrandize it ſelf, they were content to abandon him, and let the French king weaken him as much by the taking from him by compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Breſſe, Beaugé, Verome,</hi> and <hi>Gol,</hi> on the other ſide of the Alpes, as might ballance what he had added to his ſtate in <hi>Italy,</hi> by the taking of <hi>Salulles:</hi> peace being concluded upon the conditions of that exchange in <hi>Lions,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> did begin to ſee, that his alliance with <hi>Spain</hi> was an honorable burthen, and a golden chain, which did capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the liberty of his houſe, whereupon his wife being dead, he did ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bury in her tomb the beſt part of his affections towards <hi>Spain,</hi> but he did not fall off quite, in regard of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who being of Spaniſh extraction,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119672:53"/>did naturally incline to the houſe of their mother. Not long after his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſon <hi>Philip Emanuel</hi> died in <hi>Spain,</hi> not without ſome ſuſpition of help, and the miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> did often miniſter unto him occaſion of diſcontent, ſo that at the laſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to forſake thoſe who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken him, and betwixt <hi>Monſieur de Bethunes,</hi> who was then Ambaſſador for the French king at Rome, and the <hi>Count di Verrua,</hi> who was Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor there likewiſe for the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> a Treaty of confederation and alliance was concluded betwixt <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth and <hi>Charles Emanuel,</hi> The death of the French king inſuing ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, the affaires of <hi>France</hi> did change face, and the reciprocal marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages contracted betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> did exclude the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> from hope of having the eldeſt daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>France,</hi> which had been promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his ſon, or being aſſiſted with the protection of that crown, yet would he never depart from the Treaty made with <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many unkindneſſes received from <hi>France</hi> in the beginning of the reign
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119672:53"/>of king <hi>Lovis,</hi> but ſtill hoping beyond hope, <hi>&amp; injurias ferendo &amp; gratias agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> he did in the end compaſſe all his deſires, with the death of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſchal <hi>d' Ancre,</hi> all animoſity againſt him was laid aſide, and not long after he obtained the ſecond daughter of <hi>France</hi> for the Prince of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> then was he and his houſe incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into <hi>France,</hi> and that union hath ſince been ſtrengthened by the declaring of the Prince Cardinal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of the French nation in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the marrying of Prince <hi>Tomaſo</hi> unto <hi>Madamoyſelle de Soiſſons.</hi> Now he and all his ſonnes are openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the French party, and with Prince <hi>Philibert</hi> there did die all the affections of the houſe of <hi>Savoy</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Spain.</hi> This part of the world doth owe unto <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> the diſcovery of one great ſecret, which is, that the Spaniards are reſiſtible in <hi>Italy;</hi> for he did make his party good againſt them when not a ſword in all Europe was drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them but his, and they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed againſt him all the power of their Monarchy. <hi>Marcellus</hi> was the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119672:54"/>firſt that did make the Romans ſee <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibalem potuiſſe vinci,</hi> and after he had once beaten him, he ever thrived. The Spaniards have ſped little better in theſe parts, ſince the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy</hi> appeared againſt them; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> did govern all the Princes and ſtates of <hi>Italy,</hi> with <hi>tale la ment dellè; es menes ter mortifica tal Principe, &amp; di caſtigare tale Republicar</hi> now they do ſpeak the language of Chriſtians, and do recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves unto thoſe whom heretofore they did deſpiſe. If <hi>France</hi> do not abandon him, he will be a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thorn in the ſide of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards; for he hath an undaunted courage, infinite experience, incredible vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, an active ſpirit, an able body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the proportion of his years, the love of all ſouldiers, the affections and hearts of his ſubjects, inventions to finde money as faſt as he doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence it liberally, and which doth crown his happineſſe, all his children of both ſexes, beſides their incomparable fillial obedience, and ſingular vertues, have abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to govern a far greater ſtate then his: ſo that fearing no diſorder in his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119672:54"/>own houſe, he may adventure ſafely his perſon abroad, where he is kliewiſe nobly ſeconded by two of his ſons. His pretentions are great, unto <hi>Savona,</hi> the Marquiſat of <hi>Final,</hi> and many other places, and he doth hope with this occaſion to advantage his houſe in ſomething, whereupon he hath without ceremony pulled off his mask, and being the firſt that hath entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the liſt, he will be the laſt that ſhall retire.</p>
                     <p>Although I have juſt cauſe to fear, that this disjoynted diſcourſe may ſeem tedious to your Majeſty, yet muſt I needs in all humility crave leave to adde one word of application, which together with all the reſt I do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit unto the conſideration of your Majeſties wiſdom.</p>
                     <p>In the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, the Italian Hiſtories of that age, did with a conſtant ſtile give him the title of <hi>Protettore della liberta d' Italia,</hi> and yet it doth not appear that he did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver directly imbrace the protection of this province, or intereſt himſelf in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119672:55"/>any of their quarels, onely the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did reap notable benefit by his withdrawing himſelf out of the League of <hi>Cambray,</hi> and all the reſt had their eyes upon him, becauſe he was a contrepefo betwixt the two kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> As the affaires of the world do ſtand now, that title cannot but be derived unto your Majeſty, if you will be pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, for your Majeſty is now the riſing ſun, whom all in theſe parts do worſhip, and without any coſt or trouble your Majeſtie may take to your ſelf as much honour from the Protection of theſe princes and ſtates, as may not be a burthen unto you, and yet advantage your own affaires elſe where. Of <hi>Florence, Mantova, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena, Parma, Genova,</hi> and <hi>Luca,</hi> your Majeſtie ſhall not need to take further notice then by a gracious anſwering ſuch reſpects of obſervance, as perhaps ſome of them may ſhew unto you, for as things do ſtand now, they are not <hi>ſui juris,</hi> and at no time can any great uſe be made of them for your Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. With the Pope your Majeſtie doth hold no correſpondence, and yet
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119672:55"/>Rome is a place upon which your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſervants had need to have a vigilant eye, for there are forged all deſignes pernitious to your Majeſties dominions, and all myſteries of ſtate, which are afterwards acted in ſeveral ſtages of Chriſtendom, are firſt attired in that attyring houſe. In the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi> your Majeſties ſubjects ſhall always finde entertainment conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto the correſpondence, that ſhall paſſe betwixt your Majeſtie and the king of <hi>Spain.</hi> There do remain onely the Venetians and the Duke of <hi>Savoy;</hi> theſe do properly retain their full liberty, and are able to do your Majeſtie ſervice, and to offend any that ſhall be your enemie. By their means, and with the help of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and ſubjects, your Majeſtie may know whatſoever is done at Rome, and ſingular uſe may be made of their friendſhip, without any coſt or trouble: for the Venetians will never deſire more then to have their Ambaſſadors kindly uſed, and that the world may ſee, and take notice, that your Majeſtie doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect them, and if upon fit occaſions
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119672:56"/>your Majeſtie will be pleaſed to favour the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Piedmont</hi> with ſome horſes and dogs, they will be proud of ſuch a token of your love, and be ready to deſerve it. Your Majeſtie doth already inherit the affections and devotion both of the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> and of the houſe of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy:</hi> and when they ſhall caſt themſelves into your armes (as now they will do) if you be pleaſed onely to imbrace them, they are yours fot ever.</p>
                     <p>I will here conclude with my hearty prayers unto Almighty God, for the preſervation of your Majeſties ſacred perſon, and your daily increaſe in happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and proſperity, and ever reſt</p>
                  </div>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Majeſties moſt humble faithful and obedient ſubject and ſervant J. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119672:56"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119672:57"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119672:57"/>
                  <p>A DISCOVRSE upon the proceedings OF THE <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>SWEDEN</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1655.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119672:58"/>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:119672:58"/>
                  <head>THT PROCEEDINGS OF THE <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>SWEDEN</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a received Poſition, that all great conqueſts have proceeded origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally from the North, and terminated in the South, which point Mr. <hi>Bodin</hi> doth exemplifie very well in his Method, and confirm with a paſſage of ſcripture, <hi>omne ex Aquilone malum.</hi> In ſtead of <hi>Conqueſts</hi> put <hi>Incurſions</hi> &amp; in ſtead of <hi>All, moſt,</hi> &amp; then thim axime may paſſe, but under cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119672:59"/>that paſſage of ſcripture is miſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, &amp; not to be admitted in this ſenſe. The King of <hi>Sweden, Guſtavus,</hi> hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly added a new example to confirm the old poſition, and if his proceedings be underſtod as <hi>Incurſions,</hi> and not as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts,</hi> they will have perfect conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with the firſt generally received po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
                  <p>He did firſt paſſe the Baltick ſea, with an army of no great conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and did hazard himſelf upon ſome diſadvantages; for he could not land upon any ground, which he was not firſt to diſpute with his ſword, and was to incounter at his beginning with <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> who having many yeers ſucked the blood of poor Martyrs in that Country, would not render it without hazard of their own. Put into his balance the land troups which he had in <hi>Pruſſia</hi> and <hi>Livonia,</hi> I will confeſſe, that the hope of joyning with them (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were far off) did incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him and his naval army, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture upon an enterpriſe that was little better then deſperate, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he did well know, that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119672:59"/>were hated in thoſe parts for the cruelties and extortions which they had committed a long time, and that he ſhould be received of all good Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots as a Protector of the publick liberty, yet was he to break the ice of himſelf, there being none that did dare to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in his favour, untill he had no need of the favour of their appearing. It is more then eight years ſince the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts have looked toward the North, preſuming (and with good ground) that if they could be Maſters of the Rivers and that ſea, all <hi>Germany</hi> was to be at their devotion. None went further then <hi>Valleſtein,</hi> who did ſerve his Maſter well, and loſe nothing by the bargain. This was the onely man, to ſpeak humanly, that could have ſtopped the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; for the Emperour having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto him the inveſtiture of the Dutchy of <hi>Mechelbourg,</hi> he was able of himſelf to have maintained his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; but the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and the Catholick league having conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Emperour at the laſt Dyet of <hi>Ratiſbone</hi> to licence him, he retired to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119672:60"/>
                     <hi>Prague,</hi> and <hi>Tilly</hi> having the general command under the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> did not care to fortifie the maritime places of <hi>Pomerany</hi> and <hi>Mechelburg,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did belong to <hi>Valleſtein,</hi> whoſe ruin the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> did ſeek, and if <hi>Tilly</hi> could have been ſure that the king of <hi>Sweden</hi> would have contented himſelf with the reintegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Dukes of <hi>Mechelbourg,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Pomerany,</hi> and what with the Imperialiſts had gotten in the Dutchy of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> he would never have appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as an enemy, there being nothing that the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and he did deſire more then the ruin of <hi>Valleſtein,</hi> the diſcrediting the Emperour, and the exaltation of the Catholick league which might in due time authorize <hi>Bavaria</hi> to make a king of the Romans according to his own minde, and ſtampt at <hi>Munichen.</hi> Now if it be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examined, it will appear that the king of <hi>Sweden</hi> hath not ſpent ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny months ſince his departure from <hi>Sweden,</hi> and his arrival in <hi>Francony</hi> and <hi>Suevia,</hi> as the Imperialiſts did ſpend years in conquering North-wards: and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119672:60"/>the facility of his progreſſe is to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed unto the finger of God, and not unto the arm of fleſh.</p>
                  <p>This is taken <hi>pro conceſſo,</hi> that he hath aſſured himſelf of the Baltick ſea for his retraite, that he hath infranchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Pomeranie, Mechelbourg,</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein,</hi> that he hath cleared the beſt parts of the rivers of <hi>Elbe</hi> and <hi>Weſer,</hi> that he hath put the Circle of lower <hi>Saxony</hi> in ſtate of defence, ſecured the Marquis of <hi>Brandebourg,</hi> ſaved the Duke Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> from utter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſeated himſelf of the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks of <hi>Bamberg,</hi> and <hi>Werteberg,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the Landgraves of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> and diſpoſed the capital Imperial Towns of <hi>Francony</hi> and <hi>Swevia</hi> to accept him as Protector of the common liberty. This is very much to be done in ſo ſhort a time, but it was not done <hi>ſine ſanguine &amp; ſudore;</hi> for when <hi>Tilly</hi> did ſee that the king had paſſed the <hi>Elbe,</hi> he did look that way, to ſtop his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advancing, and upon the confines of that river there did paſſe many ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters which were very bloudy, but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119672:61"/>the main battle was given near <hi>Lipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> wherein God did bleſſe the king, and our Laity did not favour Tilly. It cannot be denied but that he did the part of a brave General in that bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and in all the former rencounters, &amp; he hath now diſcovered an errour in our ordinary Arithmetick, for that Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra of his, hath ſtill multiplied by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, and he is now as ſtrong as ever he was. It is therefore neceſſary that we ſhould examin well how things do ſtand at the preſent, foreſee what is likely to inſue and deliberate <hi>quid agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In my conceit, things do ſtand yet in <hi>aequilibrio,</hi> for although much ground hath been gotten ſince the battle near <hi>Lypſwich,</hi> and the hearts of mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men are turned to our favour in deteſtation of the cruelty which the Imperial Commiſſaries have uſed; yet if the chance of the war do turn in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther battel to our diſadvantage, all that ground is loſt, and thoſe people will return <hi>tanquam canes ad vomitum,</hi> let us take it for granted, that the king
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119672:61"/>of <hi>Sweden</hi> may go into the field with twenty thouſand foot and five thouſand horſe, not counting his garriſons. He will be encountered by <hi>Tilly</hi> and <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> with as many, if not more. If the Imperialiſts get the day, we may ſay good night, unleſſe we will deceive our ſelves. If the king prevail, it is not ſo, for he pretending nothing in <hi>Germany</hi> for himſelf, but intending the repatriation of divers exiled princes, and proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed States, they will not be able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſeverally of themſelves without him, nor he be able to maintain his army, if he do give every man is due, and retain nothing unto himſelf, which may ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him to maintain both himſelf, and thoſe whoſe protection he doth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take. Herein I do finde a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty; for if he do live wholy upon the Catholick Princes, our civil diſputes will terminate in a war of religion; and if he do live upon the Proteſtants, they will be as weary of him, as they are now of the Emperour: if he do exact from both, he will be in ſhort time equally odious to both, who will ſee that they have changed <hi>Dominum
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119672:62"/>non ſervitutem.</hi> But if the Emperour do loſe the day, he will not be ſo far ſtreightned: for the reverent reſpect due unto his Imperial Crown wil alwayes keep in devotion to his ſervice, milions of ſouls, who do deteſt the barbarous proceedings of his Miniſters. Secondly, the hereditary poſſeſſions of thé houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> yeeld many men, and are of great extenſion, which none can take from them in good conſcience. Laſtly, the dominions of the king of <hi>Spain</hi> are very vaſt, and his Treaſure of ſuch conſideration, that it is a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thing to think, that he can want mony; for although he doth ſomtimee turn banquerupt, when it doth turn him to account; yet he doth alwayes finde mony for his own occaſions, and he that hath mony, ſhall never want men. His Majeſty hath ſent the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>Hamilton</hi> with forces to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> thoſe are counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballanced by the troups which the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> hath conducted in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Emperour. The ſtates may perhaps aſſiſt the king of <hi>Sweden</hi> with conſiderable troups, when they have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119672:62"/>nothing to do; but it were better for him that they had ſomething to do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Infanta will ſend as many to the Emperour as they can ſend to him, ſo that the ballance doth go equal at preſent, but for the future, we have this diſadvantage, that if we have this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, that if we be once beaten <hi>a Plat couſture,</hi> we ſhall be worſe then before <hi>Prague,</hi> and if the Emperour loſe the day, he will prove like <hi>Anteus,</hi> and riſe from the ground with new ſtrength, having a good pulſe of his patrimony, in the conſervation whereof many are intereſſed.</p>
                  <p>The point moſt conſiderable is, that of <hi>religion,</hi> which we are like to fall upon, although we are to avoid it like a rock. If inevitable neceſſity do caſt us upon that deſperate coaſt, we muſt make account, that at this preſent in <hi>Germany</hi> there is much ground poſſeſſed by thoſe who do declare themſelves on our ſide; and thus much enjoyed by our enemies declared, as may be ſeen by a ſchedule apart, which ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed into this diſcourſe.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:119672:63"/>
                  <p>If we do confine our ſelves unto <hi>Germany</hi> onely, we ſhall get little by the bargain, and if we do go out, we ſhall loſe more. In <hi>Germany</hi> the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks have this great advantage, that they do in <hi>Spiritualibus,</hi> all acknowledge the Pope, and do agree among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in doctrine and diſcipline, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we have nothing but the confeſſion of <hi>Auſbourg,</hi> which doth binde us with ſo looſe a chain, that the names of <hi>Calviniſts, Lutherans, Huſſits</hi> are ſtill in <hi>eſſe,</hi> and their, and their hatred one againſt the other, greater then of them all againſt the Catholicks. If we do go out of upper <hi>Germany,</hi> there is Great <hi>Brittany, Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and the ſtates of the united Provinces, which do come ſhort of <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> who will be againſt us when we ſhall come to that point, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this Pope be contrary in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> yet he muſt contribute what may lie in his power, to the maintaining of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, and the like muſt be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med both of the French King, and of the Venetians and Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119672:63"/>do all wiſh an abaſing of the Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aci, but will never endure the increaſe of our religion in any place where they can hinder it. <hi>Spain</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> may well be left out here, becauſe it is too well known how they do incline, and if they could agree among themſelves, perhaps the Duke of <hi>Nivers</hi> and <hi>Mantova</hi> might be their General, with his new order of Militia <hi>Chriſtiana.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have heard ſome ſay, that we muſt truſt to our ſelves, and never expect any good from Catholicks; the firſt I grant, but I denie the ſecond. I will ſay thoſe men are very wiſe that will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate how Proteſtants thorowout <hi>Europe</hi> ſubſiſt without ſupport of Catholicks; but if we can be without them, it is good, becauſe they are to us like a lake of <hi>Anecie,</hi> which doth yeeld fiſh all the yeer, but in lent, as theſe may ſerve us at all times, but when we have moſt need of them. Here we may put into our ſcale, thoſe of the religion in <hi>France,</hi> whoſe relicks are ſomething numerous, <hi>quantum ad individua,</hi> but they are
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119672:64"/>light grains, and of no greater conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſince the integrity of their body hath been diſſolved and broken, their fortifications demoliſhed, and their leaders either ſeduced or exiled, ſo ſo that nothing can be expected from them, but the aid of ſome few volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, whoſe zeal may tranſport them to offer their ſervice unto ſuch as do or may appear in this cauſe, and the prayers of the Churches, and good wiſhes of all true Proteſtants.</p>
                  <p>There is yet another thing of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſideration, which doth make for us, and that is the difference among Catholicks for civil reſpects, which wil in part help to counterpoiſe the miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings of our religionaries in <hi>Germany,</hi> of which before I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; though <hi>France</hi> hath not hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo viſibly aſpired to an univerſal Monarchy, as <hi>Spain</hi> is ſaid to have done, (perhaps unjuſtly) it is apparent that their perpetuall domeſtick broville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have hindered them from execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and perhaps from projecting any ſuch vaſt deſignes. But it is certain,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119672:64"/>that either envy, or emulation, or reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal jealouſie have bred ſuch an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy betwixt thoſe two nations, that though they are unwilling to break, yet they will alway diſagree, unleſſe the crucifying of our Saviour do recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate.</hi> This emulation of theſe two Crowns doth breed as great a diſtraction of the Catholick body in Europe, as may be equivalent to the diſunion of our body in <hi>Germany,</hi> only herein they have the advantage of us, that their quarels being purely ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil are more accommodable of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that they have the Pope for <hi>Padre communé,</hi> unto whom they do willingly remit the arbitrement of their differences, when they are both ſo weary of making war that they do not care upon what conditions any peace be made <hi>pro interim;</hi> whereas our differences in matter of religion, are more irreconcilable; for although the parties may agree in the ground of a Confeſſion, yet differences of opinions do prove conſcientious in matter of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and opiniaſtretes in thoſe who do every one of them abound in their own
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119672:65"/>ſence, can never be reduced to temper, much leſſe to regularity, eſpecially there wanting a head on our ſide, who might call an univerſal Councel, and by coactive power inforce conformity unto what ſhould be decreed by the major part of Princes.</p>
                  <p>I do not bring in the king of <hi>Poland</hi> into any part of our account, becauſe although it be wel known he doth ſtand affected, yet it is certain that he hath onely <hi>voluntatem liberam &amp; poteſtatem ligatam</hi> at this preſent, ſo that he can do no great hurt, nor good.</p>
                  <p>There is an other circumſtance which doth make againſt us, namely, that the preſent viſible ſupportation of our cauſe doth lie upon the king of <hi>Swedens</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon onely, whom none but God can ſecure from Aſſaſſinates; and if he ſhould miſcarry, we ſhould be to ſeek, whereas the Imperialiſts, and Catholicks have more ſtrings to their bow then one. But in caſe God do protect him from treaſon intended, and that he do give him farther victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he cannot but live with ſome little
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119672:65"/>anxiety, for fear leſt the king of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> retaining the memory of old quarels, ſhould come behinde him, and that the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> ſhould fall from him, and accommodate with the Emperour. Agaiuſt theſe I have no graines of civil conſiderations to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but muſt hope that God who hath made choice of him to fight his battles, will alwayes aſſiſt him from open and ſecret enemies, and either by him, or ſome other whom God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will chuſe, will perfect the work that he hath begun.</p>
                  <p>If this model of the preſent ſtate of affaires be juſt, or doth come neer unto rectitude, then in the ſame glaſſe which doth ſhew unto us the preſent face of things, we way foreſee what is likely to be the event, as far as any thing may be conjectured <hi>de futuris contingentibus,</hi> the certainty of which is known onely to God, All that can be ſaid in this ſubject, muſt be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced unto two heads; namely the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation of all differences, all ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or the continuance of the war;
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119672:66"/>this being to be underſtood onely of <hi>Germany,</hi> which Province at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is the onely <hi>Sedes belli,</hi> it is hard to ſay which of theſe two is the moſt likely to inſue in the firſt place; for although it may be granted, that peace is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on both ſides, yet the concluding thereof will prove a hard reſultate; firſt in regard of the proximity of the armies, which can hardly be contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from enterſchaking when they come to a reaſonable diſtance; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in regard of the diſperſion of the armies, which being divided in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces far off, cannot eaſily agree upon a ſurſeance of armes univerſal, if any ſuch thing ſhould be accorded in any one place: Thirdly, becauſe neither the one party nor the other can long live <hi>en gros</hi> upon the Paiſant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt <hi>es loigne</hi> themſelves, or diſpute their bread with their ſwords. Fourthly wee do not heare as yet of any Mediator, neither can we know where to finde one that may be truſted of both parties.</p>
                  <p>for although the French king would
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119672:66"/>perhaps derive unto himſelf that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, yet the animoſity that he hath and doth ſtill expreſſe againſt <hi>Spain</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> will hinder him from being truſted by them, and the partiality that is diſcovered in him toward <hi>Bavaria</hi> and the Catholick League will make him ſuſpected by us. This office would ſtand beſt with his Majeſty, if he were not in a manner a party; for although in this conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture he might interpoſe very oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely betwixt the king of <hi>Sweden</hi> and the Auſtriaci, yet <hi>Bavaria</hi> and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick electors will hardly admit of him for what doth concern their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts. the one in regard of the <hi>electorat &amp; Palatinate,</hi> the others in regard of difference in religion, The peace or truce in the low Countries, will prove a knotty piece of work, and without that the peace of <hi>Germany</hi> can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be concluded; Again there is an other dfficulty in regard of a new war likely to begin in <hi>Italy,</hi> which will cauſe the French to diſturb the quiet of the Auſtriaci in <hi>Germany</hi>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:119672:67"/>as much as they ſhall be able, and to traverſe likewiſe any Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the low countryes: Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> having now with <hi>Tilly</hi> the command of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial or Catholick army, it is likely that they will both incline to war, the one to purchaſe the electorate of <hi>Brande-bourg</hi> (which is promiſed unto him) and the other to have his revenge, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been beaten.</p>
                  <p>All that can be ſaid on the other ſide, is that both parties may be ſo weary of the war, that they may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſire Peace upon any conditions then hazard new Battles, which are journiaillers. Secondly that the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Palatinate whereupon the quarrel is grounded, may ſeem unto ſome of eaſy belief to approach near un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the point of accomodation, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Spain</hi> hath undertaken to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Emperour on the one ſide (how reall I know not) and that <hi>France</hi> doth ſeem willing to diſpoſe <hi>Bavaria</hi> on
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119672:67"/>the otherſide, to accommodate with us upon any reaſonable conditions.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly that the Abbate <hi>Scaglia</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in his hands the negotiation of Peace or Truce with the States of the united Provinces, it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed that he may effect as much as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ney</hi> did heretofore.</p>
                  <p>If theſe Landmarks be not miſtaken, we may conclude that in probability <hi>&amp; quoad hominem</hi> it is more likely that the war will continue then any Peace be agreed upon, and therefore taking that for granted, it will now be time for us to take into conſideration <hi>quid agendum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But before I enter upon that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I will in one word mrake <hi>quid non agendum,</hi> namely, that we be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aboue all things not to break off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Treaties that are or may be ſet on foot for the accomodation of the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate how captious and eluſory ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they may be, it being good to keep
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119672:68"/>them up, as long as they do do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe us, and that we do not truſt unto them but put in lucro any benefit that may unexpectedly come by them, and therefore it will be very neceſſary to diſpoſe the king of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> not to ſtir as yet, nor to appear in perſon (as he doth ſeem to intend) for very good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects and conſiderations.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that to much paſſion be not expreſſed on our ſide in favour of the Queen mother, or Monſieur, un-until our preſent negotiations here be conſummated (which will be very ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>fait ou failli</hi>) and that we may ſee more clearly how they will govern themſelves towards the king of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> which will be a ſhort work, conſidering that their aſſiſting of <hi>Bavaria</hi> will be a ſecourſe of <hi>Piſa,</hi> if it be not ſpeedy, and that both the king of <hi>Sweden</hi> and the States do call upon them now very inſtantly for 5000. livers due unto each at the end of this moneth, and therefore theſe wil prove good <hi>pietre di parangona,</hi> and make us ſee how their pulſe doth beat.</p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:119672:68"/>
                  <p>The territories and Citties of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Papiſts in <hi>Germany,</hi> are at this preſent ſo interming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, (moſt of the Princes of each Religion having in their poſſeſſion ſome places of the contrary party) that it will be difficult to make an accurate Geomatrical diviſion, and diſtinction of them.</p>
                  <p>The chief places which the Proteſtants do at this time poſſeſſe, and in which there are few or noe places which are Catholick are,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Swede. Livonia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Norwegia. Pruſſia</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Marquiſate of <hi>Brandenbourg,</hi> Upper and Lower <hi>Luſatia,</hi> (enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the Duke of <hi>Saxsony</hi> by the Emperour, and now regained by the Kings of <hi>Sweden</hi>)</p>
                  <p>The Dutches of <hi>Pomeranta,</hi> and <hi>Mechle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Denmark.</hi>—All <hi>Holſatia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Circles of the upper and lower <hi>Saxony,</hi> in which are compriſed the Electoral Dutchy of <hi>Saxony:</hi>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:119672:69"/>and other Principalities belonging to the houſe of <hi>Saxony,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Dutchies of <hi>Lunembourg</hi> and <hi>Brunſwich,</hi> (although the lower circle be much mingled is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be accounted Catholick) Eaſt Freſland, <hi>ſc.</hi> the County of <hi>Emden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Oldenbourg—Thuringues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Marquiſates appertaining to the houſe of <hi>Brandenbourg, ſc. Bey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuch, Culembach,</hi> and <hi>Onoleſbach,</hi> or <hi>Anſpac.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Part of the Circles of <hi>Franconia</hi> and <hi>Swabe,</hi> in which are compriſed the Cities of <hi>Norimberg, Vlm, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digen, Francfort,</hi> and divers others though much intermingled.</p>
                  <p>The whole Dutchy of <hi>Wittemberg:</hi> wherein there are oney two or three Citties in which the Emperour and <hi>Bavaria</hi> have Garriſons.</p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:119672:69"/>
                  <p>Part of the Marqviſate of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Dutchy <hi>deſdeux Ponts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Counties of <hi>Hannaco.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Divers Counties upon the Confines of Alſatia, belonging to the houſe of <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Wettaraw, wherein are divers Countries the moſt of which have lately caſt off the yoke which <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> had laid upon them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heſſe</hi> of <hi>Caſſel.</hi> and <hi>Marbourg.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Part of the Dutchies of <hi>Berke; Mark, Iuliers</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>leves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The city of <hi>Straſbourg,</hi> and the terito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries adjoyning,</p>
                  <p>As for the Imperial towns, they are compriſed in the Circle of <hi>Saxony, Franconea,</hi> and <hi>Swabe;</hi> of which I make no mention here, neither do I make mention of the <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> which may alſo be eſteemed ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:119672:70"/>
                  <p>All the formentioned Provinces (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking in <hi>Swede, Narwegia</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> which are in a manner Peninſulaes) contain in latitude from the Baltick ſea, as far as <hi>Franconia</hi> (where the King of <hi>Swed</hi> is at this preſent) fourſcore Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Leagus. In longitude they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from Eaſt <hi>Freeſland</hi> to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Poland,</hi> running along by <hi>Pruſſia</hi> and <hi>Livonia,</hi> a hundreth and five and thirty leagues; of which fifteen make a degree.</p>
                  <div type="list_of_rivers">
                     <head>The Principal Rivers are,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ems</hi> which diſchargeth into the Ocean at <hi>Emden.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Weſer</hi> that diſchargeth it ſelf into the ſea at <hi>Bremen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Elue</hi> which diſchargeth at <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Rehein</hi> which paſſeth into the Ocean through the united Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119672:70"/>of the Low Countries.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Trave</hi> which enters into the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſea at <hi>Lubeck.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Oderſpree,</hi> and other Rivers which enter into the Baltick ſea at <hi>Starl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſund.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Viſtule</hi> which enters into the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſea at <hi>Danſk.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="list_of_provinces">
                     <head>The chief Provinces which the Catholicks have are,</head>
                     <p>The kingdom of <hi>Bohemia</hi>
                     </p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Siletia.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>The kingdom of <hi>Hungaria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Carinthia, Croatia,</hi> and other Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the Hereditary poſſeſſions of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Stiria</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tirol</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Carniola.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Moravia.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:119672:71"/>
                     <p>Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Saltſbourg.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Upper and Lower <hi>Elſace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bavaria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Upper and Lower <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Biſhoprick of <hi>Spires</hi> and <hi>Wormes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Treves.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Colen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Ments.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Divers Biſhopricks and other places, which as alſo the Biſhopricks and Archbiſhopricks above mentioned are contained in the Circles of <hi>Franconia, Weſtfal a,</hi> and of the <hi>Rhein.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe kingdoms and provinces, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in Latitude a hundreth and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119672:71"/>twenty German Leagues, and in Longitude (according to the Largeſt account) a hundred and forty.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
